<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An historical discourse, briefly setting forth the nature of procurations, and how they were anciently paid, with the reason of their payment; and somewhat also of synodals and pentecostals: with an appendix in answer to an opposer. By J.S.</title>
            <author>J. S. John Stephens.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1057_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872382</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169004</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169004)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 156:E1057[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An historical discourse, briefly setting forth the nature of procurations, and how they were anciently paid, with the reason of their payment; and somewhat also of synodals and pentecostals: with an appendix in answer to an opposer. By J.S.</title>
                  <author>J. S. John Stephens.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 146, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R. Hodgkinson, and are to be sold at the Rose and Crown in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Jo. Stephens.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "tevens" has been added after the "S" on the title page; "Feb: 1st 1660"; the second 1 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Union Theological Seminary, New York (Early English Books), and the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Finance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church tax --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Hiſtorical Diſcourſe, Briefly ſetting forth the nature of PROCURATIONS, And how they were anciently paid, with the reaſon of their payment; and ſomewhat alſo of SYNODALS And PFNTECOSTALS: With an APPENDIX in anſwer to an Oppoſer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> J. S.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. Hodgkinſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimo</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octobr.</hi> 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>PErlegi Libellum, cui Titulus [<hi>An Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall Diſcourſe, Briefly ſetting forth the nature of Procurations, &amp;c. By</hi> Jo. Stephens] quem fieri publicum non indignum cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeo. Imprimatur modò intra tres menſes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROBERYUS PORY <hi>S. T. P. Reverendiſsimo in Chriſto Patri ac Domino D. Archiepiſcopo</hi> Cant. <hi>Sacellanus Domeſticus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:3"/>
            <head>REVERENDISSIMO in Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Patri, ac Domino D. <hi>GULIELMO,</hi> Providentia divinâ <hi>Cantuarienſi</hi> Archiepiſcopo totius <hi>Angliae</hi> Primati, &amp; Metropolitano. <hi>REVERENDISSIMO</hi> etiam in Chriſto Patri, ac Domino D. <hi>ACCEPTO</hi> eadem providentia <hi>Eboracenſi</hi> Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo, <hi>Angliae</hi> quoque Primati, &amp; Metropolitano. <hi>Nec non</hi> Admodùm Reverendis in Chriſto Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus ac Dominis D. <hi>GILBERTO,</hi> divinâ etiam providentia Epiſcopo <hi>Londinenſi, &amp;</hi> D. <hi>BRIANO</hi> Epiſcopo <hi>Wintonienſi:</hi> Caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſque Reverendis Epiſcopis, &amp; Praeſulibus utriuſque Provinciae in Eccleſiâ Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licana conſtitutis.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nnus praeteriit vigeſimus (Reverendiſsimi &amp; Rè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verendi Partres) ex quo Tractatum hunc Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum
<pb facs="tcp:169004:4"/>de Procurationibus Synodali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; Pentecoſtalibus in Uſum publicum compoſui: ſed priuſquam ederetur Procellâ appropinquante manum ab editione retrahere cogebar, &amp; chartulas abdere a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giario qui in ſequente Tempeſtate apertâ fronte graſſabatur. Sub ſpe tamen fore tempus, ut hae meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones qualeſcunque (ſi <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarent) in lucem emitterentur. Et nunc tandem foràs exiturae Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinium veſtrum. Honorabile (vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantiſsimi <hi>Navarchi</hi> qui ad Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum Eccleſiae ſedetis) humiliter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorant. Dentem invidiae non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formido (tenuitati non invidetur, ſed ſublimitati) Contemptus eſt quem potius vereor a quo ſub um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braculo tantae authoritatis &amp; emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiae,
<pb facs="tcp:169004:4"/>velut ſub <hi>Aegide Minervae</hi> (veniâ ſubmiſſe petitá) me recipio, &amp; abſcondo. Orta fuêre annis ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actis diſsidia quàm plurima, Lites e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam &amp; velitationes de tempore in tempus non paucae inter Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conos <hi>Glouc.</hi> &amp; Clerum ibidem de Re ſolutionis Procurationú &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuum Eccleſiaſticorum; Ad quas componendas, &amp; ne Eccleſia quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam detrimenti caperet, ne etiam flamma diſſentionis inter Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos de integro exurgeret aut erum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret: Egomet ipſe inter mille mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus lubens ſurrexi. Et quid in his conatibus meis praeſtiterim in medio reliqui a peritioribus penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum.</p>
            <q>Eſt quadam prodire tenus ſi non da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ultra.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Opt. Max.</hi> qui poteſt rependat vobis quicquid a me rependi non poteſt; Et benedictiones in ſinus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros ampliſsimos magis magiſque cumulatiſsime refundat. Faxit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuper, ut peracto hujus vitae curri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo, a terrenis ad ſedes ſempiternas inter Coelites poſt ſeros annos feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer transferamini. Et haec, ex inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis ipſius votis qui eſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Paternitatum veſtranum Servulus humillimus</hi> Jo. Stephens.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:5"/>
            <head>To the Candid and ingenuous READER</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith little encouragement to undertake, and leſs abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to perform a task of this nature; I have out of my reſpect to the Clergie (whoſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling I much honour) adventured to run the hazard of a Cenſure. But as <hi>he that obſerveth the Wind ſhall not ſow,</hi> as the Wiſe man ſpeaks;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.</note> And as he that feareth oblatration muſt not travel, as all men know:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 27.15.</note> So muſt he reſolve to caſt away his pen that will not reſolve <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (to uſe
<pb facs="tcp:169004:6"/>St. <hi>Lukes</hi> Metaphor in another ſenſe) to bear up againſt the Wind of detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Thus much I can truly ſay, that <hi>Peace</hi> diſturbed, only that, (my ſelf being therein ſometime a Patient) hath ſet me now on work, and made me here an Agent, endeavouring by the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of an erroneous cauſe (the ground of ſuch diſturbance) to remove for the future (as much as in me lieth) a very ill effect ariſing thence. And albeit the light be dim, that forceth it ſelf tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a cloud of ſuch imperfections, as <hi>I</hi> muſt needs acknowledge: yet is the Greek Proverb true (and <hi>I</hi> apply it only to the unſtudied in the preſent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Better a little light,<note place="margin">Michael A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtol. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb. Cent. 11.</note> though but a very little, then none at all, better then to be altogether in darkneſs. For my part
<pb facs="tcp:169004:6"/>what <hi>I</hi> have received <hi>I</hi> freely commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate: the greater burdens <hi>I</hi> leave to the greater bottoms. All that this little Tractate hath to pride it ſelf in (were it lawfull for it to boaſt) is that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (not an innovation but,) a Novelty. Which being ſo,<note place="margin">Act. 17.21.</note> it may haply take an Athenian eare (ſo much in former times delighted with news, is the Greek Orator obſerves,<note place="margin">Demoſthen. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epiſt.</note> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him St. <hi>Paul;</hi>) yea an Engliſh one too, if it be with the Engliſh now as it it was in <hi>Gildas</hi> his time. <hi>Patria mea novi ſemper aliquid audire volens, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith he. But what it is, how and with whom it will take, I have not to ſay. This only <hi>I</hi> know, that it hath proved (weak as it is) to my dull apprehenſion, the iſſue of more than ordinary labour, ſome part of it, there
<pb facs="tcp:169004:7"/>being none <hi>de cujus lumine, lumen accenderem meum;</hi> None whoſe footſteps <hi>I</hi> could find (though <hi>I</hi> thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſought) to follow in ſo unfrequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a deſert as <hi>I</hi> wandered through.
<q>
                  <l>—quá nulla priorum,</l>
                  <l>Caſtaliam molli divertitur or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita clivo.<note place="margin">Virgil. Georg. 13.</note>
                  </l>
               </q> In a word, what <hi>I</hi> have here done, my thoughts have wrought within me this perſwaſion, that the ſame by the ingenuous Reader will be taken in good part. For the vulgar and unknowing perſons (who are least able to judge, but moſt apt to cenſure) <hi>I</hi> fear not their Arrows.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169004:7"/>
            <head>De Procurationibus.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>OC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M fuiſſe poenituit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando, ſiluiſſe nunquam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Simmidis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum apud <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch.</hi> de tuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da Valetud.</note> ſaid one, and truly, it being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to unſeaſonable and inconſiderate ſpeaking; elſe the Wiſe-man <hi>Salomon</hi> will teach us ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Leſſon, <hi>That as there is a time to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, ſo is there alſo a time to ſpeake;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.7.</note> and whoſoever ſhall ſpare either Tongue or Pen, when in probability he may doe good, omits a neceſſary duty, and doubtleſs incurs deſerved blame. How neerly this Caſe did once reflect upon my ſelf, they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169004:8"/>beſt know, whoſe oppoſition to pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (juſt as I conceive) hath ſtirred me up to ſtrive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as they wont to ſay) to the uttermoſt of my power, as well to give them ſatisfaction that pay, as to procure eaſe to thoſe that receive. An opinion hath of long time poſſeſſed ſome of the Clergy, That <hi>Procurations</hi> are only due <hi>Ratione viſitationis,</hi> and that without reſpect unto ſuch Act of <hi>Viſiting,</hi> no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, of that nature, can be in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence warranted or payment by Law en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, and therefore Arch-deacons to be excluded in the years of Epiſcopall Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Upon this miſtaken ground (for ſo I take it) ſuits have formerly been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced, and much time and money ſpent, and yet the point remains unſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the Clergy (moſt of them) pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this due (whileſt the ſame was paya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to the Arch-deacon (eſpecially in the Lordbiſhops <hi>Triennials</hi>) with a kind of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy, <hi>mixta voluntate,</hi> as I may ſay, and many deſiring <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate. The ttuth is, and I finde it ſo,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169004:8"/>That payments, how neceſſary and juſt ſo ever, yet are they not at all times pleaſing to thoſe upon whoſe ſhoulders they lie; they being of ſuch a nature as to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man is <hi>unpleaſing,</hi> to wit, <hi>burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi> mainly oppoſing the principall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the natural deſire,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theogn. ſent.</note> namely <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Liberty.</hi> They are in the Law called <hi>One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra;</hi> and by ſo much the more <hi>Oneroſa</hi> burdenous and unpleaſing they are, by how much the more the reaſon to evidence the true ground and originall cauſe of them is unknown to ſome that pay. To lighten therefore this Load, what I may, and for the eaſe of ſuch as being preſſed with the burden of their Miniſterial functions, and Eccleſiaſticall imployments; their thoughts buſied and their Studies taken up and converſant in the Sphere of higher ſpeculations) have not leiſure to look into things that move in a more inferiour Orb: I have put my ſelf forward (but to ſpeak truth <hi>actus eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) to ſearch into the nature of ſome of thoſe Church-payments, and dues Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169004:9"/>namely <hi>Procurations, Synodals,</hi> and <hi>Pentecostals,</hi> and have endeavored to find and diſcover the true reaſon of their pay, begun ſo long agoe in the Church, and continued to this day; which how far forth I have performed in this little Tract I leave to the judgement of the judicious Reader;<note place="margin">Euripid. in He raclid. pa. <hi>287.</hi>
               </note> reflecting upon my ſelfe, and ſeriouſly wiſhing in this particular taske, what the ſervant in <hi>Euripides</hi> wiſhed to old <hi>Iolaus</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith hee) that I alſo were as able to perform, as I have been willing to undertake the ſame; however I proceed, and begin with <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curations.</hi> In the handling of which point I ſhall neceſſarily fall upon the ſeverall enquiries following, namely, Firſt
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>What a</hi> Procuration <hi>is, Whence ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, And how, And in what manner it was anciently paid?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Whether due</hi> ratione Viſitationis?</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Whether only, ſo due, and no otherwiſe?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, we have two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169004:9"/>things to conſider of, to wit, the <hi>quid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> and the <hi>quid rei.</hi> For the <hi>quid nominis,</hi> I have not found much written, ſomwhat I have; That the word hath its derivation a <hi>Procurando,</hi> there is no doubt of that, but procuring what, there is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Whether it ſhould be for procuring the <hi>Viſitor</hi> to come to each particular Church in his own perſon, and to Viſit <hi>Eccleſiatim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pum. E. concil. Toletan. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>per cunctas Dioeceſes parochiaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuas,</hi> which was the ancient cuſtome; Or from procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him to come to a certain place in ſeverall Diviſions or Deaneries, where the Clergy within the ſaid diſtinct Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries were to give meeting, as now they doe, they being overcharged with his coming home to them; each man may pleaſe himſelfe with his own opinion? For my part, I cannot ſatisfie my ſelf with either of them. My reaſon againſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is; <hi>Viſitation</hi> is a principall duty that belongs unto every Biſhop (derived from the Apoſtles, who were Viſitors,<note place="margin">Act. 15. Act. 16.</note> and did <hi>pertranſire Eccleſias &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbes</hi>) it ſticks in his very name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which comes from a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169004:10"/>word that ſignifies to Viſit <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">So alſo from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>viſit co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</note> and is frequently uſed in that ſenſe, not only in the Scripture, but alſo by Eccleſiaſticall and Prophane Authors, obvious every where to be met withall.<note place="margin">Epiſcopus deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t viſitate ſingulis annis Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, niſi dimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat propter gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vamen Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; tunc mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conum, &amp;c. Ab. Sic. ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>2.1.</hi> de Oſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chid. c. ut Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chidiaconus. <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Decrevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp;c. Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pum. <hi>2</hi> Coke. <hi>15.</hi> D. Spelman. Concil. pa. <hi>238.</hi>
               </note> Now to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Viſitor by way of ſtipulation and contract, to doe that which by his calling and place, either in his own perſon, or by others (himſelf being hindred) he ought to doe, is a plain <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſtands with no reaſon or congruity, if I may judge.</p>
            <p>And as weakly built (if I miſtake not) is the other opinion, to wit, That <hi>Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> ſhould have their denomination from pocuring the Viſitor to come to a certain place in every Deanery or Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas it is evidently manifeſt,<note place="margin">Ext. de Cenſibus c. Cum Apoſtolus &amp;c. Foe icis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordationis eod in <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> that the word <hi>Procuration</hi> was then uſed when the Viſitor viſited <hi>Eccleſiatim,</hi> as may be ſeen in divers Chapters in the Canon-Law.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon then is to be ſought for to give the word its true genuine inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, as it relates to the preſent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169004:10"/>and that is, not from procuring the Viſitor by way of contract to come; no, but from procuring of victuals for him and his attendants, when they come in Viſitation. Thus it was, and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed comes neer unto the nature of the word <hi>Procurare,</hi> (which among other ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications it hath) ſignifieth to nouriſh, and to make proviſion in diet for;<note place="margin">Dua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris, Eccl. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. &amp; Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hoc autem munus ideo Procuratio vocatur quia Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae Epiſcopum Procurant, id eſt Curant, alunt ac tuentur; ſicut pueri dicuntur Procurari a Nutricthus &amp; equus a Domino apud</hi> Plautum <hi>&amp; al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os Authores Latinos qui propriè &amp; emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè locuti ſunt.</hi> Thus <hi>Duarenus:</hi> But here now comes a Cloud in our way that muſt be a little cleer'd before I goe farther, leſt I ſhould hold the Reader (the Reader I ſay unverſed in this ſtudy) too long in a miſt of ſuſpenſe. And objection may be made thus. Were victuals antiently the Viſitors pay, for and in reſpect of Viſitation? why then doth the ſecond Councell,<note place="margin">Concil. Bracar. <hi>11.</hi> Can <hi>2.</hi> Concil. Toleta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>7.</hi> Con. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> held at <hi>Bracar,</hi> above a thouſand yeares agoe, and the ſeventh Councell held at <hi>Toledo</hi> in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169004:11"/>
               <hi>Spayn,</hi> a little after, expreſly forbid by their Canons, That no Biſhop <hi>per ſuam Dioceſim ambulans,</hi> ſhould receive ought from the ſeveral Churches within his Dioces, <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honorem Cathedrae ſuae,</hi> that is to ſay, two ſhillings;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> ca. inter caetera <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi gloſſa in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſu.</note> To this I anſwer, out of the Gloſſe upon the Decree where the Canon of the ſeventh Councell at <hi>Toledo</hi> is recited. The Caſe there is This. The Biſhops of the Province of <hi>Gallicia,</hi> when they viſited their Dioceſſes, hardly preſſed upon their viſited Clergy: Bringing with them a great Train of attendants (100 <hi>vel</hi> 200 <hi>Equitatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi>) and exacting from them not only, <hi>ultra duos ſolidos pro Cathedratico,</hi> but alſo coſtly proviſion in <hi>eſculentis &amp; poculentis;</hi> upon complaint made of this grievance the Councell decrees a moderation in the money receipts <hi>(Ne ultra duos ſolidos exigant pro Cathedratico)</hi> and for the number of Attendants they are reduced to fifty at the moſt, and the time of their ſtay at each Church limited to one day, and no more, So that this Canon is no bar at all to our <hi>Procuration</hi> payment in money now, 'tis I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169004:11"/>dare boldly ſay a meer <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to that purpoſe: For it was many years after this time that money had war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to paſs for viſitation Procurations, as I ſhall hereafter, God aſsiſting, make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident: ſo that the Objection being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and the <hi>Quid nominis</hi> in ſome ſort explained, I proceed to enquire, deſirous more exactly to know what a Procurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in the <hi>Quid rei.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vallenſ. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. de cenſibus, §. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And to this enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Vallenſis</hi> makes anſwer, and tells ut that it is <hi>Neceſſariorum ſumptuum exhibitio quae ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Viſitationis debetur ab Eccleſia, vel Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio ei cui ex officio incumbit jus &amp; onus Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi, ſive is ſit Epiſcopus, ſive Archidiaconus, ſive Decanus, ſive Legatus ſummi Pontificis.</hi> I hus <hi>Vallenſis;</hi> and well for the ground of this Procuration due, but not fully e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the growth thereof, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now other reaſons not included with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the circumference of this deſcription, that inforce the payment of Procurations without viſitation, as I ſhall in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of this diſcourſe (I doubt not) make appear. Wherein for further expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169004:12"/>of <hi>Vallenſis</hi> his deſcription, I ſhall be bold to aſſert that the <hi>Quid ret</hi> of viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Procurations in ancient time, this <hi>exhibitio neceſſariorum ſumptuum</hi> was victuals. In the Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> (I doe not mean the great General Councel under <hi>Innocent,</hi> the Third, but that other under <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third,<note place="margin">Exe. de Cenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus c. Cum. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſomewhat above 30. years before, and about the year of our Lord 1180.) Viſitors are directed ſo to proceed in the diſpatch &amp; execution of their Viſitations as thoſe that minded not their own things, <hi>ſed quae Jeſu Chriſti.</hi> And it follows there, <hi>Nec ſumptuoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s epulas quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant, ſed cum gratiarum actione recipiant quod honeſtè ac competenter illis ſuerit miniſtratum.</hi> Thus there: ſo in the Sext there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution made by <hi>Innocent</hi> the 4. (who came in Pope, <hi>Anno</hi> 1243.) and ratified af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by a General Councel held at <hi>Lions</hi> in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Tenth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 1273 peremptorily;<note place="margin">C. <hi>1.</hi> §. Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationes, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xigit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od in <hi>60.</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi Gloſſa in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (yea <hi>ſub poena maledictionis aeternae</hi>) forbidding the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of money in lieu of Procurations <hi>(vel a volentibus ſic ſolvere)</hi> adding moreover,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169004:12"/>that if any Viſitor ſhould preſume to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them in ſuch ſort, and otherwiſe then in victuals: <hi>Duplum ejus quod receperit Eccleſiae a quâ id receptum ſuerit infra menſem reddere tenebatur;</hi> which if accordingly (be ing Patriarch, Archbiſhop, or Biſhop) he failed to reſtore, he was forth with liable to an Interdiction, <hi>ab ingreſſu Eccleſiae:</hi> But for Viſitors of inferiour ranck, ſuſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>ab officio &amp; beneficio</hi> was their penalty in this caſe. This then was the ancient man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of paying Procurations till the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, who ſucceeding in the Popedome about twenty two years after the death of <hi>Gregory,</hi> and finding <hi>multa incommodorum diſpendia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſ. in ver. diſpendia c. Foelic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dationis cod. in <hi>6<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </note> many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencs in the Conſtitutions of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor touching this particular, did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf make a Conſtitution about the year 1295. that it ſhould be lawfull to any Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor whatſoever <hi>volentibus viſitatis,</hi> and not otherwiſe, to receive in lieu of victuals money (not to exact it) towards the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraying of their viſitation charge. The Conſtitution runs thus, <hi>Quoniam rerum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perientia
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169004:13"/>perientia nos inſtruxit ex hoc tam perſonis viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantibus quam l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cis &amp; Eccleſiis viſitatis multa in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodorum diſpendia provenire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">C Foelicis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſupra in <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Concedimus ut Patriarchae, A chiepiſcopi, &amp; al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i quibus ex offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio competit viſitare a volentibus Eccleſiarum &amp; locorum Viſitatorum Rectoribus, ſeu perſonis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniam licitè recipere valeant pro ſumptibus mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratis faciendis in victualibus di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus quibus viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationis officium perſonaliter exercebunt.</hi> Now the reaſon of the making of this conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was out of queſtion this, namely in reſpect of the great charge that the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Clergie were put unto in giving enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment to the Viſitors in thoſe times, who in their viſitations came attended with a troup of men and horſes ſo exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively great,<note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. de Cenſibus c. Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Apoſtolus</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t interdum Eccleſiaſtica orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ſubditi exponere compellebantur.</hi> The poor Clergi were eftſoons conſtrained to ſell even their Church-ornaments to make proviſion for them, as it was declared o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in the aforeſaid Councel of <hi>Lateran.</hi> And thereupon in that Councell all Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors came to be ſtinted to a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Viſitation Attendants, according to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169004:13"/>their ſeverall qualities, as namely the Archbiſhop to 40. or 50. men with their horſes, the Biſhop to 20. or 30. Cardinals to 25. (though it ſtick in their ſtomachs ſo to be undervalued) Archdeacons to 5. or 7. Deans,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in v. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cani. Ext cod. c. Cum Apoſtolus. Ext. av. Com. de Cenſibus c. Vas electionis.</note> (that is to ſay <hi>Archipresbyteri rurales,</hi> as the Gloſſe expounds it) to two only, which qualification of number ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a little, and but a little, the burden that was ſtill heavy upon the Clergy. For though <hi>Bomface</hi> did tolerate the receipt of money in heu of victuals, and made it lawfull for the Viſited to compound with their Viſitor for their entertainment, yet the compoſition in money was oftimes upon ſuch hard terms, that the remedy proved as bad as the diſeaſe. Little the better were the Clergie for having the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor limited to a certain number of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, whileſt he was left unlimited in the ſumme of his receits to make his compoſition as it pleaſed himſelf: Yea, we ſhall find that the exorbitances of the Viſitors in this particular were ſuch, that they gave occaſion to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169004:14"/>Fifth to complain bitterly of them in the Councel at <hi>Vienna</hi> (which began in the Calends of <hi>October,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ca. Ad noſtrum eod in Clement Antiquit, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. pa. <hi>172.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>11, and ended upon the ſixt of <hi>April,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloff in v. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſterum c. Cum ſit in Clem. de Cenſious</note> the year following, as the Gloſſe preciſely ſets it down) name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the Prelates and other Viſitors did exact <hi>Procurations,</hi> yea even from exempt places and Orders priviledged (the Ciſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians themſelves could not goe free) that they carried with them Hounds and Hawks contrary to a Prohibitory Canon of the aforeſaid Councel of <hi>Lateran,</hi> yea that they ſo farre forth proceeded with them, that unleſſe their intemperate appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite were ſatisfied, and that they had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily miniſtred unto them as much as they unreaſonably required; down went the dores of Monaſteries, Church dores were broke open, and what they could lay hands on (the ornaments of the Church not excepted) ſhould away, <hi>Intolerabilia gravamina eiſdem cumulantes.</hi> Now theſe grievances were in effect but complained of in this Councel; and altbeit they were prohibited under pain of Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169004:14"/>yea and of the Popes too,<note place="margin">Ca. Ad noſtrum cod. in Clement.</note> yet were they not throughly redreſſed until the time of <hi>Benedict</hi> the Twelfth, who next ſucceeded <hi>Clement,</hi> ſave <hi>John</hi> the 23. that came between them. He, I ſay, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into conſideration the abuſes of the Viſitors towards the Clergy viſited (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding many good Laws made to the contrary) namely that they became ſo burdenſome to them in the exaction of <hi>Procurations, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t oppreſsi ſubditi hujuſmodi onera nequeant ſupportare,</hi> to uſe the very words of the Conſtitution.<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trav. Com de Cenſibus c. Vas I lict onis.</note> In the ſecond year of his Popedome, and about the year of our Lord, 1337. makes a Canon or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and in the ſame proportions a rate in money in lieu of Procurations in victuals, a certain ſumme payable out of Monaſteries, Priories, and other Churches viſited, and requirable by the Viſitor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his quality and the conditions of the parties viſited, more or leſſe, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it ſtill to the liberty of the viſited, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to pay ſo much money or victuals as before, if they thought better. And this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169004:15"/>conſtitution of <hi>Benedict</hi> the Twelfth, put an end to that troubleſome buſineſs even throughout the Chriſtian world (where the Pope had ſway of juriſdiction) that before that time groaned under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of intolerable exaction. Hither all Viſitors are directed to have recourſe for their pay, where cuſtome hath not limited the ſumme of their receipts. But for Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons Procurations, <hi>Lindewood</hi> tells us that the uſuall ſumme of their receipts in money was in his time (and that was in the reign of <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. ſomewhat above 200. years agoe) ſeven ſhillings and ſix pence, that is, according to the number of his Officers and Attendants to each man 12. d. and to the Archdeacon himſelf 18 d. And ſo I have done with the firſt <hi>Quaere,</hi> and doe now proceed to the ſecond, and that is.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Whether Procurations be due,</hi> Ratione Viſitationis?</p>
            <p>Out of doubt they are, and great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that they ſhould be. The voice of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169004:15"/>nature in an Heathen man ſpake thus, and perſwadeth to yield <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Phocy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id.</note> And not only the voice of nature but the God of nature pronounceth,<note place="margin">Luc. 10.7. 1 Cor. 9.</note> that <hi>Dignus est o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perarius mercede, Luc.</hi> 10. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thus. <hi>Who goeth to warfare any time at his own coſt? who planteth a Vineyard, and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of the fruit thereof? who feedeth a flock and eateth not of the milk of the flock? If we have ſown unto you ſpirituall things, is it a great matter if we reap your carnall things?</hi> Thus the Apoſtle excellently, and by way of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie to the equity of this due, brings ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments ſuch as the wit of man cannot move, much leſs overturn them: For what are Viſitations other then laborious travellings from place to place, joyned with an induſtrious vigilancy and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection in the Viſitors, and for this very end, <hi>Ne quid detrimenti capiat Eccleſia;</hi> to keep Chriſts Vineyard from havock and ſpoil, to ſee unto aſwell the building and holding up of the ſpirituall Temple, as the fabrick of Gods materiall Houſe. He plants, he ſows, he feeds, his labour is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169004:16"/>painfull, and his care great, and all to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radicate ſin, and to encourage virtue. In a word <hi>Schiſmata componere</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Caetera diſponere,</hi> that all things may be done <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.14. In a word thus,<note place="margin">Act. Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. <hi>24.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Viſitationum omnium iſtarum praecipuus ſit ſcopus ſanam orthodoxamque do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam expulſis haereſibus inducere, bonos mores tueri, pravos corrigere, populum cohortationibus &amp; admonitionibus ad religionem, pacem, innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> accendere.</hi> So the <hi>Trent</hi> Councel (I would in all things ſo) right and well. And long before that Councel, <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third our of the aforeſaid General <hi>Lateran</hi> Councel declaring the right uſe of a Viſitation,<note place="margin">Ext. de Cenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ca. Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationes.</note> ſets it down thus: <hi>Porro vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitationis officium exercentes non quaerant quae ſua ſunt, ſed quae J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſu Chriſti, praedicationi &amp; cohor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationi, correctioni &amp; reformationi vacando.</hi> So then this being, as you ſee, a burdenſome and a toylſome task, a labour of pain ſo neceſſary, and withall conducing to ſo good an end. It is but juſt that ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable compenſation ſhould be made, ſome exhibition yielded to the Viſitor, by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169004:16"/>him or them who principally are intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the good of his travell. Neither ſtands this payment or exhibition upon conveniency only, but neceſsity alſo. There is a <hi>debetur</hi> in it, ſaith <hi>Vallenſis,</hi> upon which the Viſitor founds his claim, and ſuch a <hi>debetur</hi> as admits of no oppoſition or ſtop in Law to croſſe it; for the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holds ſtrong,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in ver. Conſuetud. c. Cum ex oſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii, Ext. de Praeſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iptioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Ext. de Cenſibus c. Cum Venerabilis.</note> 
               <hi>Epiſcopus cum viſitare jure communi debuerat, de jure communi debet habere tune Procurationem, quia nemo ſuis ſtipendiis cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur militare.</hi> Here is the reaſon of the due! And it is a rule in Law, that <hi>Acceſſorium ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur naturam ſui principalis.</hi> And if <hi>ex debito principaliter</hi> the Biſhop or Viſitor ought to viſit, then <hi>ex condigno acceſſorie</hi> he ought to receive, no man will deny; for a neerer relation there ſeems not to be between work and wages, then is between Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Procuration; yea, ſo near they are, that no negative preſcription, to wit <hi>de non ſolvendo</hi> hath been held available in plea or proof at Law againſt the right of Procuration, eſpecially as it relates to Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, except in the caſe of Papall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169004:17"/>or extreme poverty of the viſited.<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in c. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabili v. rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable, Ext. de Cenſious.</note> In the Decretalls mention is made of a certain Archbiſhop, namely the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Sens (Senonenſis)</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rench Prelate,<note place="margin">Exteod. e. ex Offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> that viſiting of his Province, he came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Churches of the Abbot of St. <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore,</hi> and of the Prior <hi>de Caſtres,</hi> and of ſome others in the Dioceſs of <hi>Paris,</hi> which he viſited, <hi>&amp; eâratione</hi> demands Procurations, which were denied him for this cauſe, namely for that they had not formerly been yielded to the Predeceſſor of the ſaid Archbiſhop. Hereupon the Archbiſhop proceeds, and ſuſpends all that ſtand out, and refuſed to ſatisfie his juſt demands; and afterwards upon their further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt excommunicates them, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third with what he had done: Who preſently writes to the Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> letting him to know, that foraſmuch as againſt Procurations due <hi>ratione viſitationis</hi> no praeſcription ought to be admitted, as neither againſt a viſitation it ſelf, although both might haply in reſpect of time be preſcribed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169004:17"/>
               <hi>Ideoque mandamus</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>quatenus ſententiam quam in bujuſmodi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptores de antiqua Metrapolis conſuetudine tulit Arthiepiſcopus memoratus uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factionem condignam factas obſervari.</hi> Thus Pope <hi>Innocent.</hi> And after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner did <hi>Honoriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Third write on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of another French Biſhop (to wit the Biſhop of <hi>Maine (Cenomanenſts)</hi> which Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in v. non ſolverunt c. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabili, Ext. de Cenſibus. &amp; ibi textus.</note> as I ſuppoſe, is within the Dutchy of <hi>Anjow</hi>) complaining againſt the Abbat and <hi>Covent de Cultura</hi> of his Dioceſs that refuſed to pay him Procurations in his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, alledging this for their reaſon, <hi>Quod ipſi hactenus Procurationem non ſolverunt,</hi> which being not admitted for a good plea, the ſaid Pope reſcribes thus: <hi>Diſcretion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae</hi> (writing to the Abbats <hi>de Tyron</hi> and <hi>Joſaphat,</hi> his delegates in that cauſe) <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus quatenus niſi aliud &amp; rationabile oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derint, vos eos ad exhibendum eam ſicut jus dictarverit compellatis.</hi> To this effect <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ext. de Cenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c. cum nuſer.</note> and after him <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth ſends out his <hi>Mandate</hi> to the ſame purpoſe through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Province of <hi>Benerventum</hi> in the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169004:18"/>of an Archbiſhop there. We may conclude therefore out of the Canon Law, that Procurations are due, and ought to be paid <hi>ratione viſitationis.</hi> And ſo I have done with the ſecond <hi>Quaere.</hi> The third and laſt is,</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Whether Procurations be only due</hi> Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne viſitationis, <hi>and no other wiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, not ſo only, though principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo. The Canoniſts <hi>ex hypotheſi</hi> propound this queſtion, namely, that if a Church be ſo neer unto the Viſitor that there needs no travel, and ſo little or no labour is beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the viſitation thereof whether a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curation may lawfully be required from that Church? And albeit the queſtion be negatively held by ſome, yet by the moſt it is affirmatively anſwered,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in ver. peragrando. §. ulterius apud Lancellotum Inſt. juris Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. l. <hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>21.</hi> ubi de Cenſibus. Hoſtienſ. ſum. de Cenſibus, §. a quibus.</note> namely, That <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatio ſolius laboris in tuitu non exhibetur, ſed etiam in ſignum ſuperioritatis, &amp; ut facilius Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lati ad viſitandum inducantur:</hi> So that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the viſitors pains be but little, and his charges nothing at all, yet is not the Procuration for that cauſe to be leſſened,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169004:18"/>it muſt be yielded notwithſtanding, <hi>in ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſuperioritatis.</hi> But to come neerer to the point, <hi>Boniface</hi> the Eighth, of whom mention is made before, writing to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain one whom he had appointed his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, to gather up a Tenth from all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Livings, and perſons through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Jtaly</hi> and elſwhere, for the maintenance of a warre he proſecuted in the Kingdome of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and intimating to him whom he would have charged, and whom excuſed, ſaith thus, <hi>De illis autem Proourationibus quas Praelati in pecuniâ numeratâ rite percipi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt ab antiquo, &amp; quas perciperent, ettamſi non viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarent decimam praeſtare tenentur.</hi> And again,<note place="margin">Extrav. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. de Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis c. Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones.</note> 
               <hi>Praelati autem qui Procurationem quam ſine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatione potuit de jure percipere in pecuniâ nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meratâ, &amp;c.</hi> By which it is manifeſt that there is <hi>Procuratio ſine Viſitatione;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ext. de Cenſibus c. quanto. Gloſſ. in. v. Viſitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis c. Piocura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, ext. cod. C. Ad nostrum eod. in Clem. C. vas electio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cod in Fx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant. Gloſſ. in v. non ſolverunt, c Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerab. ext. de Cenſibus.</note> But what Procuration is here praeciſely meant may fall into queſtion. To which I anſwer, that I find mentioned in the Canon Law divers kinds of Procurations, ariſing from diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reaſons; as namely firſt from <hi>Viſitation,</hi> ſecondly <hi>Pact,</hi> thirdly <hi>Priviledge,</hi> fourthly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169004:19"/>and laſtly <hi>Custom;</hi> all which, as they did ariſe from different reaſons, ſo were they paid at the firſt in a different manner. Victuals were anciently and ſolely the viſitation <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curation</hi> till this Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> his time who made money paſſable in lieu of victuals for that payment. The reſt, as I conceive, were all paid in money; ſo then the Procuration from whence the Pope was to have a Tenth, being in <hi>pecunia numerata,</hi> and being then <hi>ex antiquo, et de jure,</hi> in that ſort due, as in the Text is evident: And money for viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation Procurations, but even newly tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to paſſe: both <hi>Viſitation</hi> and <hi>Custome</hi> too as preſcribed from that right, are quite excluded from the cauſality of this pay in this place, as i take it. It is probable then, that from one of the other Reaſons of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curation</hi> the Tenth before ſpoken of was requirable, but for which of them, as it is not much materiall on my part curiouſly to ſeek after, ſo neither is it of conſequence for any to know, there being at this time no <hi>Procuration</hi> from any ſuch cauſe, to wit, of Pact or Priviledge, in uſe of receipt in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169004:19"/>this Kingdome, that I know, or have yet heard of. That which I intend, and aim principally at in the ſolution of this third and laſt <hi>Quaere</hi> (and is of frequent uſe in theſe times) is to ſet forth the claim that <hi>Cuſtome</hi> makes, and the right that ſurely it hath to this Eccleſiaſticall payment of <hi>Procurations ſine Viſitatione.</hi> To make good therefore the receit of <hi>Procurations</hi> by this reaſon, we are firſt to ſet down the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all properties required in a prevailing Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, which, in ſhort, are chiefly two: The firſt is, that it be <hi>rationabilis:</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, that it be <hi>legitimè praeſcripta.</hi> Now that Cuſtome is ſaid to be <hi>rationabilis,</hi> and ſo conſequently <hi>inviolabilis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſ in v. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionabilis. c. Cumtanto. Ext. de Conſurtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Diſtinct. <hi>11.</hi> c. Conſuetud. &amp;c. Eccleſ. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt tutionum.</note> 
               <hi>quae nec diviuo juri contradicit, nec obviat Canonicis inſtitutis,</hi> that contradicts not the divine Law, nor meeteth the Canonicall Inſtitutes in the front of oppoſition. And that is ſaid to be <hi>legitimè praeſcripta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſ. in ver. uſque ad boc tempus, c. ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitium <hi>18.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> when <hi>bona fide</hi> it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for the ſpace of 40 years, If theſe two, to wit, Reaſonableneſs and ſufficient continuance of time doe meet together in a Cuſtome, they make that Cuſtome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169004:20"/>impregnably ſtrong. As on the contrary, upon the want of Rreaſon it is as eaſily overturned, though never ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient by that known rule in the civil Law.<note place="margin">Paulus l. <hi>29.</hi> H. de Regulis juris.</note> 
               <hi>Quod initio vitioſum eſt non poteſt tractu temponis convaleſcere;</hi> and that in the Canon Law,<note place="margin">C. non ſirmatur <hi>18.</hi> de Regulis juris in 6<hi rend="sup">o</hi> &amp; Dyn. ibi.</note> 
               <hi>Non firmatur tractu temporis quod de jure ab initio non ſubſiſtit,</hi> there being no Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of ſuch praevaling authority, <hi>ut aut Rationem vincat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In l. <hi>8.</hi> tit. <hi>32.</hi> C. Quae ſit longa Conſuetudo.</note> 
               <hi>aut Legem,</hi> as the Emperor well determines. Now they that turn upon this hinge, I mean that receive Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curations upon the ground of Cuſtome, muſt look that their receit or claim be both <hi>rationabilis &amp; legitimè praeſcripta.</hi> And this appertaineth eſpecially to ſuch Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons that receive Procurations in the L. Biſhops <hi>Triennials,</hi> and yet viſit not, whereof there are divers in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Certainly the time was, that Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons had <hi>jus viſitandi quolibet anno,</hi> and did accordingly viſit, <hi>&amp; ea ratione</hi> receive Procurations,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. Lind. in c. <hi>1.</hi> in ver Viſitation. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc. Conſtitut. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſic. Archid. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> the Gloſſe upon the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Conſtitutions intimates as much. And in the Decretals <hi>de officio Archidiaconi,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169004:20"/>we read that Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3. wrote unto the Biſhop of <hi>Coventry,</hi> and to the Abbat of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and commands them to forbid the Archdeacon of <hi>Cheſter</hi> to viſit the Churches within his Archdeaconry above once a year,<note place="margin">Ext. de offic. Arch d. c. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus &amp; Gloſſ. ib. in v. ſoepius viſitare.</note> 
               <hi>Niſi talis cauſa emerſerit propter quam ipſum oporteat praefatas Eccleſias ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius viſitare.</hi> Once a year and no more, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi talis, &amp;c.</hi> which implies that once a year at leaſt he might; ſurely in ages paſt he might doe ſo:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But Time that turneth all things upſide-down, &amp; makes them ſeem to be what they were not, hath altered the courſe of former dayes, and brought it now to this iſſue, namely, that the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons (not all, but of many places) muſt one year in three ſuffer the light of Archidiaconall authority to be eclipſed by the greater light of Epiſcopall power, and content themſelves with their Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations only, which yet the Clergy in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places think much to pay, in reſpect not only of the many payments that lie heavy upon them (wherein thoſe of the meaner ranck are much to be pitied) but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169004:21"/>eſpecially becauſe the Archdeacons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands at that time doing no ſervice at all, ſeem to them to be altogether unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. For the receit then of Procurations by Archdeacons in the years of Epiſcopall viſitations, when ſome of them viſit not; and to make the Cuſtome by which they receive them firm and good. They are firſt, as before is ſaid, to ſhew ſufficiency of cauſe and reaſon for this receit, to make it <hi>rationabilis;</hi> and next to ſet forth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of continuance to make it <hi>legitimè prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripta.</hi> In explication whereof, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to our preſent buſineſs, I intend to be very brief, beginning with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part or property of a good Cuſtome, namely Reaſonableneſs. But with ſerious proteſtation in the firſt place, that I labour not by any argument to introduce a pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that hath not formerly been, or to impoſe a burden heretofore not known or born; for that were in effect to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and to meddle with things that ought not by any private fancy to be moved or meddled withall, that were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169004:21"/>little elſe then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Iſocrates.</note> foibidden by the Oratour as perilous in a well ſettled State. No, but my endeavour ſhal be to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch reaſons as I can for payméts now in uſe in places where they are uſed, and to ſtretch out the line of my diſcourſe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which if they prove to be of weight, it may haply fall out, that what formerly the Clergy (to their great charge) contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting this payment, have in <hi>contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio judicio</hi> been forced to pay, and what at this day they pay, though diſcontentedly, as being conquered rather by Law, then fully ſatisfied in point of reaſon, they will with a willing mind <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12.</note> readily, chearfully, and peaceably tender to their Viſitor. I o proceed then; Procurations are in effect the Living of the Archdeacon valued to him in the Kings books, for which he payeth yearly Tenths, and Subſidies alſo, as they fall out to be due. And ſhould a man yearly pay, and not yearly receive? No, for the contrary to be the intent and meaning of the Kings and Queens of this Land may
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169004:22"/>evidently be demonſtrated:<note place="margin">Et ulterius de ampliore gratiâ noſtra exonera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus &amp;c. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatnm—de omnibus &amp; om nimodis Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis, Reddit. feod. annuitat. penſionibus, por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus, &amp;c. Praeterquam de —de eadem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoria de—ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eun', ac Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacono de— &amp; ſucceſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus ſuis pro Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationibus &amp; Synodalibus Annuatim ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vend. &amp;c.</note> For that in ſuch Grants, as I have ſeen from the Crown of Impropriate Rectories, thoſe payments (annuall payments) of Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſo of Synodalls too, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and left as a charge (though many other burdens are taken away) upon the Proprietaries. Again, whereas many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſticall Livings, ſince the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate of their value into the Exchequer about the 26 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. are improved and made better; <hi>Procurations</hi> are like the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hid in the napkin, they continue without one farthing improvement. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement doe I ſay? Nay, I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that few Archdeacons receive in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curations to the ſumme of their valuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Poverty ſomtimes of the Incumbents death, and ſuch by blows, cuts them ſhort of many, and makes them heartleſs, to ſeek where little or nothing is to be found. And yet are they charged with full payments of Tenths and Subſidies, which are high upon fruits of this nature; for valued by the penny as theſe Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169004:22"/>are, 5 <abbr>l.</abbr> out of 50 <abbr>l.</abbr> goeth out for Tenths alone: And ſhall a man pay, pay thus, and not receive? ſurely he that is neceſſitated to pay, ſhould neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (and doubtleſs with good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he may) that which occaſioneth and is the ſole reaſon of his pay; yea, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of Procurations in this caſe is ſo farre from being unconſcionable in the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon, though he viſit not, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of them ſeems to me to be unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; For in that the Archdeacons ſome of them (I ſay ſome of them,<note place="margin">Ab. ſic. ſuper <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> i</hi> de officio Archid, c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Archidiaconus.</note> for all are not excluded) viſit not in the L. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops <hi>Triennialls,</hi> the fault's not theirs, when not out of willfull omiſsion, but Canonicall ſubmiſsion, they forbear to viſit, and ſtrike ſail to the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ſuperiors: And ſhall they for their obedience be deprived of their accuſtomed rights? I leave that to the judgement of indifferency. The Rule of Law, and ſurely of Reaſon too, is,<note place="margin">Ca. Imputari <hi>41.</hi> de reg juris in <hi>6<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putare non debet ei per quem non ſtat, ſi non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat quod per eum fuerat faciendum.</hi> A man in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169004:23"/>the Law is not held to be faulty for omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to doe what by his ſuperiour he is not permitted to doe. Nither is it of weight (as I conceive) that ſome urge, That foraſmuch as all Archdeaconries, or the moſt part of them have their corps, to wit, ſome ſpirituall dignity or promotion appendant to them, the Archdeacon that hath ſuch Corps ought to live upon it in the years when he viſits not, and out of the profits ariſing thence (poor and <hi>jejune</hi> perhaps) to ſuſtain and defray the whole charge of the Archdeaconry. It is true that many, yea moſt Archdeaconries have their Corps annexed to them, but none that I know <hi>ſine ſarcina,</hi> none but hath its peculiar payments and charge of Tenths, Subſidies, or Penſions, or all together ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant, even to the full, as much, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more then any other Eccleſiaſticall Living of that nature. And to charge them with more then their own burden (which is found of times heavy enough) would be ahard impoſition, to ſpeak the leaſt. But eſpecially, if it ſhould ſo happen that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169004:23"/>Archdeacon had no other means (as ſuch there have been as well in this Kingdome, which I could name, as in forein parts,<note place="margin">Duaren. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> de ſacris Eccleſ. miniſteriis &amp; beneſiciis.</note> as <hi>Duarenus</hi> doth remember) then were it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed intolerable, and the rather in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects eſpecially: Firſt in reſpect of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for therein conſidered he is a perſon of ſpeciall and remarkable Quality. Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in reſpect of the Office that he ſuſtains,<note place="margin">Ab. ſic. ſuper ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda prim. de offic. Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e b. c. ut Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chipresbyter.</note> which is <hi>Dignitas principalis poſt Epiſcopum in Eccleſia:</hi> and upon which there is, at leaſt in former times there was, ſo much dignity appendant in regard of the amplitude of power and juriſdiction that he had under the Biſhop, that <hi>Philip,</hi> a fifth Son of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Groſs King of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lus Aemili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Tilius.</note> diſdained not to take upon him the Office of an Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con in <hi>Paris,</hi> as Stories tell us. And for ſuch a one to want correſpondent accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ext. de Office. Archid. C ut Archidiacon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ad bae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Onuphr. Pantan. Int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rpr. vocum Eccleſiast. in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Chron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui ad Platin. de vitis Ponuſ. p. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> a moſt unſeemly &amp; abſurd thing. He is called <hi>Oculus Epiſcopi, Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus circumlustrator &amp; perſcrutator. Vicartus post Epiſcopum ad quem in omnibus in Clero om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cura pertinet,</hi> with ſuch like Titles of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency. Now ſhould he be deprived of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169004:24"/>his juſt rights, it would come to paſs that his care would be ſo much to provide ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries for himſelf at home, that he ſhould find little leaſure <hi>circumluſtrare,</hi> to look into the field of the Church, and to take care for others abroad. But I know with whom I have to doe, they are Scholars whoſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to apprehend a reaſon and ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to acknowledge a right, I truſt will prove ſuch, as that I ſhall not need to beat more ground for reaſons; which yet were there cauſe, I could eaſily add to give them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in this point, namely of the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs</hi> of the Archdeacons receipts of Procurations in the L. Biſhops Triennials. I deſcend therefore to the other property of a prevailing Cuſtome, namely, <hi>Sufficiency of Continuance,</hi> whereof in a word.</p>
            <p>It hath been <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra hominum memoriam,</hi> and ſo equivalent to an Imperiall Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or Conſtitution;<note place="margin">F. de aqua quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid. &amp; coſtiva l. <hi>3.</hi> §. Ductus aquae.</note> for it is an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ſince the Certificate upon the Commiſſion of <hi>Melius inquirendum</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eccleſiaſticall Livings was returned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Exchequer, at what time it was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169004:24"/>what particular payments were year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then made to the Archdeacons of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Dioceſſes in this Kingdome out of Eccleſiaſticall Livings; and thereupon their receipts became accordingly valued in the Kings Books, and ſo ſtand unto this day. And leſt the Church by means of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Monaſteries, and other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houſes (from whence Procurations, and ſuch like dues before that time had been uſually paid to Eccleſiaſticall Governors) ſhould receive detriment, and be impeached in its former accuſtomed receipts &amp; rights, when all the Lands and Poſſeſſions of thoſe Religious Houſes were ſetled in the Crown, &amp; came into the Kings hand by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, there was afterwards another Act of Parliament in the 34 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. by which a ſtrict proviſion was made for the due pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all ſuch Eccleſiaſticall rights, as namely Penſions, Portions, Corrodies, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnities, Synodies and Proxies, that were payable to, and in the poſſeſſion of any Eccleſiaſticall perſon. Ten years before the Diſſolution, no preceding viſitation, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169004:25"/>cauſall act or motive inducing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, more then that ſuch due had accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably been paid out of the ſaid Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houſes.</p>
            <p>And thus have I runne through, and given anſwer briefly to the third and laſt enquiry, wherein I have endeavoured to prove: Firſt, that there is Cuſtome for the receipt of Procurations without viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And ſecondly, the ſame (from the grounds of Reaſon and Continuance as to that point) to be warrantable &amp; good. And to make the matter clear, I have thought good to ſubjoyn, as moſt pertinent and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory (ſuch in my opinion) to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent buſineſs, the ſubſequent Caſe of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies; which (deveſted and ſtript from its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Norman</hi> dreſſe, and clad in plain <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>) preſents it ſelf to the Readers view as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:169004:25"/>
               <head>Trin. 2 <hi>Jacobi</hi> in the Exchequer.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Caſe of Proxies</hi> Between the <hi>KING</hi> and Sir <hi>Ambroſe Forth,</hi> Dr. of the Civil Law, and one of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Chancery. The Caſe was this.</head>
               <p>THe Biſhop of <hi>Meth</hi> before the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Monaſteries had a <hi>Proxie</hi> of 15 s. 4 d. payable yearly out of the Commandery of <hi>Kells</hi> in the County of <hi>Meth,</hi> parcell of the poſſeſsions of the Hoſpital of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and another <hi>Proxie</hi> of 20 s. pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able yearly out of the Impropriate Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Trevet</hi> in the ſame County, parcel of the poſſeſsions of the Abby of <hi>Thomas</hi>-Court in the County of <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 33 year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the ſaid Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the ſaid Abbey of <hi>Thomas</hi>-Court were ſurpeſſed and diſſolved, and the poſſeſsions of both the ſaid Houſes were veſted in the actuall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169004:26"/>and real poſſeſsion of the Crown by Act of Parliament. But in the ſame Act there is an expreſs <hi>Saving</hi> of Proxies to all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their ſucceſſors. After that the Biſhop of <hi>Meth</hi> and his Clergie (for that Biſhoprick hath no Dean and Chapter) did by Deed enrolled, dated 16. <hi>Martu</hi> 36 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. grant the Proxies aforeſaid <hi>(in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alia)</hi> to K. <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, his Heirs and Succeſſors, the ſaid King being at the time of the Grant and after in actuall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of the ſaid Commandery and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, out of which the ſaid Proxies were payable.</p>
               <p>Afterwards Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> by her Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents dated 1 <hi>Novembris</hi> in the 33 year of her reign, did demiſe the ſaid Commandery and Rectory to Dr. <hi>Forth,</hi> rendring rent without any reſervation of Proxies. And whether he ſhall be now charged with the ſaid Proxies, and with the arrerages of them incurred ſince the commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Leaſe was the queſtion? and it was adjudged that he ſhould be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: and three points were ſtirred, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169004:26"/>debated in the argument of that caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether the Proxies were utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct by the ſuppreſsion &amp; diſſolution of the ſaid Religious Houſes of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi>-Court, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Saving</hi> within the Act of Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the Biſhop can grant the Proxies to the King?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the Proxies were extinct in the hands of the King by the unity of poſſeſsion.</p>
               <p>For the firſt point it was objected by the Counſell of Sir <hi>Ambroſe Forth,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that theſe Proxies were extinct by the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and diſſolution of thoſe Religious Houſes; for that the viſitation of theſe Religious Houſes was the ſole cauſe of the payment of Proxies, <hi>Et ceſſante cauſa ceſſat effectus.</hi> For thoſe Religious perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deraigned and diſperſed, were not after that ſubject to Viſitation; and then when the Viſitation ceaſed, the Proxie being alſo an exhibition given to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor, for his travelling charges ſhall ceaſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169004:27"/>alſo. For <hi>Procuratio,</hi> (as the Canoniſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it) <hi>eſt exhibitio ſumptuum neceſſariorum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta praelatis qui dioeceſes peragrando Eccleſias ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectas viſitant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet they agree that the Viſitation cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not immediately by the ſurrender, or by the Act of Parliament which giveth thoſe Religious Houſes, and their poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to the Crown: for by that their Corporations were not diſſolved, as 'tis held in the Caſe of the Dean and Chapter of <hi>Norwich,</hi> in the third part of the Lord <hi>Cokes</hi> Reports, 15. <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 8. 32 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Br. Corporations</hi> 78. But when thoſe Religious perſons were deraign'd, and had relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed their habit, rule, and order for which they were viſitable, then the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration was utterly diſſolved, and upon that the Viſitation ceaſed.</p>
               <p>And they reſembled the Proxie due for Viſitation to an Annuity <hi>pro conſilio,</hi> or <hi>pro ſervitio impendendo.</hi> If the Counſel or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice be withdrawn, the Annuity is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. So if a rent charge be granted for a high-way: ſtop the way and the Rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169004:27"/>ſhall be alſo ſtopped. 9 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.19. 15 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.2. 21 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.7. 45 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Dier</hi> 6. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.76. So alſo where a <hi>Corodie</hi> is granted for certain ſervice to be done: Omiſsion of the ſervice determines the <hi>Corodie,</hi> 20 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. <hi>fol. ultimo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Twas alſo ſaid, that this duty was not annuall, but contingent, and payable on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at every viſitation; as <hi>Eſcuage</hi> for every journey Royall; or as <hi>Aid</hi> for marrying of a Daughter, or for making a Sonne a Knight. In which laſt Caſes, if an <hi>Avowry</hi> be made for <hi>Aid,</hi> 'tis a good plea in barre thereof, to ſay that the Avowant had not ſuch ſonne or Daughter alive at the time of the <hi>Aid</hi> levied, <hi>N. N. Br.</hi> 82. <hi>g.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the <hi>Saving</hi> they ſaid, that the ſame was a <hi>Flattering Saving,</hi> which could not preſerve the Proxies in being which the Law had extinguiſhed, as it was held 14 <hi>Eliz. Dier</hi> 313. That the Tenure of Obit or Chauntry Lands held of Subjects are extinct by the Act of 1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>Saving</hi> in the ſaid Act <hi>propter abſurditatem:</hi> So the Proxies in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169004:28"/>ſhall alſo be extinguiſhed <hi>proptor abſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatem.</hi> For as it is abſurd that the King ſhould be ſubject to attendance in reſpect of Tenure, ſo it is abſurd that the King ſhould be ſubject to Viſitation, or to any duty in reſpect thereof. And of the ſame nature are many <hi>Savings,</hi> put in <hi>Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Caſe, <hi>Plow. Com.</hi> 563. which are there called <hi>Flattering Savings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond point,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it was objected, That the Biſhop could not grant the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies</hi> to the King for two Reaſons: The one deduced from the perſon of the King, the other from the perſon of the Biſhop.</p>
               <p>Firſt for the King,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> admit that he were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſuch Spirituall Office, as to be Viſitor of Religious perſons, yet ſhall be not have <hi>Proxies</hi> in reſpect of Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency and Indecency, and alſo Impoſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty; for it is not convenient or decent that theſe poor Religious perſons ſhould bear the charges of the King, and it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo impoſsible: for by the Canon Law <hi>Procuratio exhibenda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt ſecundùm qualitatem perſonae viſitantis.</hi> And the Majeſty of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169004:28"/>Kings perſon, and the greatneſs of his Train is ſuch, that by praeſumption of Law no private perſon can bear his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary charges, or make entertainment for him correſpondent to the quality of his perſon. And therefore 'tis held 27 <hi>Henr.</hi> 8.10. <hi>b.</hi> That where Common <hi>ſins number</hi> was granted to an Abbat, and his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors out of the Manor of <hi>Dale,</hi> that after the Diſſolution the King ſhall not have the Common <hi>ſans number;</hi> for it is there ſaid, that if the King have it he may ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Land, which the Law will not ſuffer. As if a Villain purchaſe Common <hi>ſans number,</hi> the Lord ſhall not have it for the reaſon aforeſaid, for then the Ter-tenant may loſe the profit of the Land.</p>
               <p>For the Biſhop,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> though lie may grant his Temporall poſſeſsions, with the aſſent of his Chapter or Clergie, yet thoſe duties that he hath by Prerogative of his Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall chair, or as incident to his Spirituall function, he cannot grant, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rule of the Canon Law are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169004:29"/>of three kinds. 1. <hi>Subiſdium Cathedraticum,</hi> which is a duty of Prerogative and Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority. 2. <hi>Quarta Epiſcopalis,</hi> which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him for the Reparation of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. 3. <hi>Procurationes</hi> for his viſitation, <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> which is a perquiſit or profit of his Spirituall Juriſdiction: as Creation mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney given to a Duke or Earl for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his honour, cannot be granted over: 6 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Dier</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p>For the third point they ſaid,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the <hi>Proxie</hi> be a perſonall thing, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able only in reſpect of the perſons viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yet admit that theſe <hi>Proxies</hi> are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come reall, and that the Commandery and Rectory be charged with the ſame <hi>Proxies:</hi> then the unity of Poſſeſsion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth them in the hands of the King. As a Lordſhip, Rent-charge, Common, and the like are extinguiſhed by the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the Tertenant, if he hath equall eſtate in the Land, and in the thing which chargeth the Land. And to this purpoſe the Caſe of 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4.19. <hi>a.</hi> was put; where 2 Prior had an Annuity out of a Parſonage
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169004:29"/>by Preſcription, the Parſonage is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to the Priory and the Annuity is extinguiſh'd for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>But on the other part it was anſwered by the Kings Councell, and reſolved by the Court.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat the ſaid <hi>Proxies</hi> were not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the Diſſolution of the ſaid Religious Houſes, but were well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and ſaved to the Biſhop.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Biſhop had well granted them to the King.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the unitie of poſſeſsion in the Kings hand did but ſuſpend, not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the <hi>Proxies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt point it was obſerved: Firſt that <hi>Proxies</hi> had not their originall in the primitive Church; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> viſiting all the Churches which he had planted in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> demanded not any <hi>Proxies,</hi> but laboured with his own hands for his maintenance, that he might not be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome to the Churches. Yet long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Canon Law, which declares that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169004:30"/>
                  <hi>Proxies</hi> are due to the Biſhops in their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations, ſaith,<note place="margin">Inſlit. Juris Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. l. <hi>2.</hi> ca. de Cenſ.</note> that it is agreeable to the doctrine of St. <hi>Paul; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t a quibus ſpirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alia recipimus eiſdem temporalia communicemus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly 'twas noted that the ſame which we call <hi>Proxie</hi> or <hi>Procuracy,</hi> is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Canoniſts <hi>Procuratio,</hi> becauſe that in overy Viſitation the perſons viſited procured neceſſary proviſion for the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors, which proviſion at the firſt was in victuals, <hi>viz. in Eſculentis &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulentis;</hi> and that was do be received with moderation and temperance,<note place="margin">Diſtinct. <hi>35.</hi> c. Eccleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne jejuniorum doctrinam ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentibus buccis praedicent,</hi> as it is ſaid in one of the Canons.</p>
               <p>But afterwards, when the pomp and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Viſitors required ſo great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions as were grievous and intolerable to Churches and Religious Houſes, then every Church and Religious Houſe was reaſonably taxed; and thereby <hi>Proxies</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a certain ſum of money payable yearly in the nature of a Penſion to the Ordinary, who had power of viſitation <hi>merojure,</hi> as 'tis ſaid 10 <hi>Eliz. Dier.</hi> 273. <hi>b.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169004:30"/>
               <p>And this was aptly reſemble to Socage in our Law, of which <hi>littleton</hi> ſaith, That in ancient time a great part of thoſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants which held of their Lords by So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage, did come with their Sokes [their Ploughs] certain dayes in the year to plough and ſow the <hi>Demeſnes</hi> of the Lord; and becauſe that ſuch workes were done for the livelyhood and ſuſtenance of their Lords, they were acquitted againſt their Lords of all other ſervices.</p>
               <p>Afterwards theſe ſervices were changed into money by conſent of the Lords &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Tenants, that is, into an annual rent. And as the Tenants in Socage after the ſaid change paid their rents yearly to the Lord, although he had aliened his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes,</hi> and had no land to be ploughed or ſowed; ſo the Churches &amp; Religious Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, after the Procurations of victuals were reduced to a certain ſum, paid them year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their Ordinary though he made no Viſitation; and ſo the Rule of <hi>Ceſſante cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſâ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceſſnt effectus</hi> holds not in theſe Caſes. And to this purpoſe directly is Sir <hi>William
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169004:31"/>Capels</hi> Caſe put in <hi>Luttrels</hi> Caſe, in my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> his fourth Report, where it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That Land being holden by a Rent payable for the keeping of a Caſtle, that though the Caſtle be demoliſhed or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, yet the rent muſt be paid: For 'tis there ſaid, That where the Tenant hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the Lord to keep or repair the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the Lord, and afterward ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice (as <hi>Littleton</hi> ſaith in the Caſe of <hi>Socage</hi>) was anciently by mutuall conſent of Lord and Tenant) changed into an annual rent, although the ſaid rent be <hi>pro warda Caſtri,</hi> yet the Lord cannot have the keeping of the Caſtle back again when he will; for after the compoſition and change made, the keeping of the Caſtle is utterly gone. And <hi>Pro</hi> imports no condition, as in the Caſe of an Annuity granted <hi>pro conſilio im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendendo,</hi> but a plain and perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence and ſatisfaction. By the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame reaſon in our Caſe, albeit that the Parſonages impropriate are now made layfee, ad are come into the hands of lay Gentlemen, which are not viſitable; and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169004:31"/>though that the Religious Houſes are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, diſſolved, and overthrown, as the Caſtle in Sir <hi>William Capels</hi> Caſe; yet the ſaid certain ſummes of money which came in lieu of <hi>Proxies,</hi> and retain the name of <hi>Proxies,</hi> and by ancient compoſition are become parcel of the certain and ſettled Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Biſhop, ſhall remain for ever, and ſhall not be ſubject to exinguiſhment, no more then Annuities, Penſions, or Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Tythes, which are paid to this day out of many Abbies &amp; impropriate Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the originall cauſes for which they were firſt granted or paid, ſhall not be now examined or brought into queſtion. And at this day the King himſelf doth pay and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Proxies</hi> out of all Impropriations which he hath in his poſſeſſion; and therefore in every Leaſe made by the King of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate Rectory, the Leſſee doth cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to diſcharge all Proxies, Synodals, Penſions, &amp;c. And Sir <hi>Humphry Winch</hi> then chief Baron (at the hearing of the ſaid Cauſe) ſaid, That before the diſſolution of Monaſteries, where a Rectory was Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169004:32"/>to an Abbey immediately the Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ceaſed as to the Rectory; for the Abbat was not viſitable as Rector for his doctrine, but as Abbat for his rule and order: And yet without queſtion the Ordinary had his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xies out of all Parſonages appropriate to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies as well before the diſſolution as after.</p>
               <p>And for the <hi>Saving</hi> in the Act de 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>ca.</hi> 5. the ſame is no idle or <hi>Flattering Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> but reall and effectuall: for it is agreed before, that thoſe Proxies were in being at the time of the making of the Act, and not extinguiſhed by the ſurrender of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Houſes; for their Corporations were not diſſolved untill the Religious perſons had relinquiſhed their houſes, and were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed. And then ſuch things as were in <hi>Eſſe</hi> at the time of the making of that Act might well be preſerved &amp; ſaved by the Act, though the things extinct before could not be revived by a <hi>Saving</hi> without expreſs words of Grant and Reſtitution. And this difference appeareth plainly in the Caſe of <hi>Kekewich</hi> 27 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Brook Parliaments</hi> 77. And in Sir <hi>John Molins</hi> Caſe in the ſixth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169004:32"/>part of my Lord <hi>Cokes</hi> Reports.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to the ſecond point it was reſolved, That Proxies in their originall nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duties payable for viſitation, were grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the King, and the King was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch grant, eſpecially when the ſaid duties were converted to a ſumme of money certain, in the nature of a Penſion or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity: for by the ancient Law of the Realm the King hath power to viſit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and correct all abuſes and enormities in the Church; and by the Statutes made in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the Crown was only remitted and reſtored to its ancient juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, which was uſurped by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> 33 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Fitz. Aid del Roy.</hi> 103. <hi>Reges ſacro oleo uncti ſpiritualis juriſdictionis ſunt capaces.</hi> And <hi>Proxie</hi> is a profit of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, 10 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Rex eſt mixta per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona cum Sacerdote:</hi> Alſo by the Common Law the King might have Tithes, of which no [meer] lay perſon is capable: 22. <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 75. 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.1. The King himſelf ſhall vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit his Free Chappels and Hoſpitals: 8. <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 29. <hi>N. Br.</hi> 42. a. And <hi>Caſſaneus in Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169004:33"/>Gloriae mundi, part.</hi> 5. <hi>conſider.</hi> 24. cites a text of the Canon Law, <hi>viz. Quòd omnes Reges dicuntur Clerie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and another text that ſaith, <hi>Quòd cauſa ſpiritualis committ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> potest Principt latco.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And where it was ſaid, that in reſpect of the greatneſs of the King and his Train, competent <hi>Proxies</hi> could not be miniſtred to him, and by conſequence could not be granted to him. This objection is taken away, in that the <hi>Proxies</hi> at the time of this Grant were reduced to ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney certain: As alſo the Rule of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law is not plainly cited before, for the Rule is <hi>Procurat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o exhibenda eſt ſecundum qualitatem perſonae viſitantis &amp; ſubſtantiam viſitatorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was further reſolved, That the Biſhop with the aſſent of his Clergie might well grant theſe <hi>Proxies</hi> to the King for that the Law hath qualified the perſon of the King to receive ſuch Grant, albeit the ſame be ſuch a Prerogative of the Biſhop that cannot be aſſigned to any other. As the Creation mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of a Duke or Earl may be granted and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169004:33"/>ſurrendred to the King, though it cannot be granted to any Subject. Alſo <hi>Proxies</hi> being now reduced to a certainty in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and ſo made parcel of the certain ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and perpetuall revenue of the Biſhop, might be as well granted by him as a portion of Tythes, or an annuity, or any of his Rents, Services, or other Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments temporall.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And as to the third point, it was alſo reſolved and adjudged, That the unity of poſſeſsion of <hi>Proxies,</hi> with the Rectories impropriate and Religious Houſes, out of which <hi>Proxies</hi> were payable, did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the Proxies in the hands of the King, but ſuſpend the payment of them only <hi>pro tempore quouſque,</hi> the King by his Grant ſhould ſever the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>For the finding of the Law in which point, the nature of theſe things was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, which in any fort might be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to drowning, or extinguiſhment by unity of poſſeſsion. And they were ſaid to be of three kinds, as</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169004:34"/>
               <p>Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Eſtates in Land.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Actions reall, and Titles to Land.</p>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Things iſſuing or coming out of Land, or taken and had upon Land.</p>
               <p n="1">Eſtates in land are properly drowned or confounded,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> when a leſſer eſtate concurs with a greater in the ſame perſon, and in the ſame right: as <hi>Terminus &amp; feodum non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt conſtare ſimul in una eademque perſona;</hi> and a pregnant reaſon thereof is put in the Caſe of <hi>Bracebridge, Piowd. Com.</hi> 3 9 b. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Term is a time finite, and Fee-ſimple is a time infinite; of neceſsity then the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite muſt be drowned and confounded in the infinite. <hi>Ob.</hi> But thats confounding, and not extinguiſhment: for if a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Tenant grant or ſurrender his Eſtate to another in Reverſion, the particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is not extinct, though it be drowned and confounded; and if a particular Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant hath charged the Land with rent or other incumbrance, the Eſtate ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in being to this intent. And in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169004:34"/>truth Eſtates in Land, and right to Land, are things of ſuch ſubſtance which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be extinct, or <hi>penitus interire.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Littleton</hi> ſaith, that if a Diſſeiſee, when his entry is taken away, releaſeth to the Tertenant all his right, that that ſhall not enure by way of Extinguiſhment; for the right that he had paſſed to the Tenant by his Releaſe. And it were inconvenient that ſuch ancient right ſhould utterly be extinct: For, <hi>droit ne poet pas morier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But things that iſſue out of the Land, as Lordſhip, Rent-charge, &amp;c. are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to extinguiſhment to all intents. As if a Lord grant his Seigniory or Lordſhip to a Tertenant and a Stranger, there ſhall be no joyntenancy or ſurvivor between them, for the moity of the Lordſhip is extinct to all intents and purpoſes: <hi>Plowd. Com.</hi> 4.9. <hi>a.</hi> And if a Lord releaſe to a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant all his right in the Lordſhip or the Land, ſuch releaſe paſſeth by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhment againſt all perſons: <hi>Littleton</hi> 112. <hi>b.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Reall actions alſo,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169004:35"/>are ſubject to extinguiſhment, and that is <hi>quaſi</hi> by unity of poſſeſſion. As in all caſes of <hi>Remitter,</hi> There, he that hath right of action for Land, hath alſo the poſſeſſion of the Land it ſelf; ſo that there is not any perſon againſt whom he can bring his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for that cauſe the action is extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed for ever.</p>
               <p>And upon the ſame reaſon, <hi>Condition</hi> which gives title of reentry in Land is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed by purchaſe of the Land, or part of it: 8 <hi>H.</hi> 7.8. <hi>b.</hi> 33 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Br. Extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 49. So warranty is extinguiſhed by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>infeoffment or Deſcent of Land to the ſame perſon that had the Warranty: 40 <hi>E.</hi> 3.13.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Things iſſuing or comming out of Land, or taken and had upon Land are of three kinds, and from thoſe different kinds of things theſe differences doe ariſe.</p>
               <p>If things have their originall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement out of Land, and no otherwiſe, and are due in reſpect of Land only, and are part of the profits of Land, ſuch things ſhall alwayes be extinguiſhed by unity of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169004:35"/>poſſeſsion; if a man hath equall eſtate and right in both together. Of this nature is Seigniory and reall ſervices: 3 <hi>H.</hi> 6.1. <hi>a.</hi> 40 <hi>E.</hi> 3.40. <hi>b. Littleton</hi> 49. <hi>a.</hi> 122. <hi>b.</hi> 34 <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 15. <hi>Rent-charge: Littleton</hi> 48. <hi>b. Dier</hi> 140. <hi>b. Common</hi> 11 <hi>H.</hi> 4.5. <hi>a.</hi> 24 <hi>E.</hi> 3.25. <hi>b. Chimin.</hi> 21 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>a.</hi> 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.3. <hi>a.</hi> And two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of this rule were brought; one, For that the thing that's extracted out of Land, when it comes back again to the Land, will be naturally extinct; for there is <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutio ad materiam primam,</hi> from whence comes naturall extinguiſhment as well of man as of all other terreſtriall things. The other more legall reaſon, is, That he that hath all profits entirely, ſhall not be ſaid to have part of the profits, for part is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in the whole; and therefore a man cannot have Seigniory, Rent, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or High way in his own land.</p>
               <p>But on the other part,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> things that are not iſſuing out of land, as parcell of the profits of land, but are otherwiſe derived and due upon other reſpect, albeit they are taken and had within certain land,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169004:36"/>yet unity of poſſeſsion doth not extinguiſh ſuch things. Of this nature are all Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes; as if a man hath a Warren or <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> in the land of another, and afterwards purchaſeth the ſame land, this unity of poſſeſsion doth not extinguiſh the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes, but he hath them in his own land: 28 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Dier</hi> 30. <hi>b.</hi> 16 <hi>Eliz. Dier</hi> 327. <hi>a.</hi> 35 <hi>H.</hi> 6.56. <hi>a.</hi> So is it of <hi>Waif, Stray, Wreck, Leet, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> though the thing be part of the profits of the land, and payable by ſuch perſon only that hath the land, yet if ſuch thing had its commencement and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall upon any perſonall reſpect, and not in reſpect of the land, and ſo the perſon only is charged, and not the land, ſuch thing ſhall not be ſubject to extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by unity of poſſeſsion: and of this nature are <hi>Annuities, Diſmes, Proxies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If an <hi>Annuity</hi> be granted in fee by apt words to charge the Heir or Succeſſor,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Heir or Succeſſor ſhall not be charged without Aſſets of the land, yet if the Grantee of the Annuity enter upon this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169004:36"/>land, that entry neither ſuſpends nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth the Annuity; for the land is not charged, but the perſon in reſpect of the land; for if the land were charged it ſhould not be an Annuity only, but a Rent-charge, and ſhould be recovered by Diſtreſs and Avowry, which remedy the Law yields not for a meer Annuity. Alſo upon aſsignment over of ſuch Annuity, Attornment ſhould be neceſſary, which needs not upon the aſsignment of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, as is noted by <hi>Yaxley</hi> 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.1. <hi>b.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This point is made more clear, 10 <hi>E.</hi> 4.10. <hi>a.</hi> An Abbat brings a <hi>Scire facias</hi> againſt a Vicar upon judgement in an Annuity, being againſt the Vicars Predeceſſor. The Defendant ſaid that the Annuity iſſued out of the Manor of <hi>B,</hi> and the Tythes, Oblations and Obventions of the Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge, which Manor and Tythes make the Vicaridge: and that the Plaintiff had made entry upon 43 acres parcel of the manor, and had taken the Tythes. Hereupon judgement was deſired, whether he ought to have execution. And the whole Court
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169004:37"/>held that it was no plea, becauſe that this recovery was upon a Writ of Annuity: for in the Writ of Annuity the perſon on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is charged and not the land; and to ſay that he had made entry upon that land, where by his ſuit it appeared that the rent iſſued not out of the land, is no plea. And it is alſo there reſolved, that in an Annuity againſt an Abbat upon the title of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, it is no plea, That the Plaintiff had entred into parcell of the poſſeſsions of the Abbey. And in an Annuity againſt an Heir, though he ſhall not be charged if he hold not by Deſcent, yet 'tis no plea to ſay that the Plaintiff had entred into the land deſcending.</p>
               <p>But 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7. the caſe is more ſtrong. A Parſon of a Church was charged with an Annuity to another Parſon by Praeſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Parſonage out of which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity was payable was appropriate to the Priory of <hi>Aliens,</hi> which Priory being ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. was granted by Parliament to <hi>H.</hi> 5. Afterward <hi>E.</hi> 4. grants the Parſonage Impropriate to the Dean of St. <hi>Stephens</hi> againſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169004:37"/>whom a Writ of Annuity is brought by the Parſon that had the Annuity by preſcription. And the Opinion of the Court was, That the Annuity was not extinguiſhed by the grant of the Parſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to <hi>H.</hi> 5. by Act of Parliament, though there be no <hi>Saving</hi> thereof, and that this Annuity is not given <hi>incluſive</hi> with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; for the Rectory was not charged with the Annuity, but the perſon of the Rector only. And albeit the payment of this Annuity might be ſuſpended in the hands of the King, yet when the King had paſſed a Grant of the Parſonage, it ſhould revive.</p>
               <p>As to Tythes,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thoſe are part of the profits of land, and doe ariſe and renew from and out of land, and yet they ſhall not be extinct by unity of Poſſeſsion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are originally due in a perſonall reſpect. For the ignorance and weakneſs of Lay perſons, which needed inſtruction and confirmation in matter of Religion, was the originall cauſe of the payment of Tythes. And the Parſon of a Church
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169004:38"/>claims not Tythes in reſpect of land, but in reſpect of the perſon of his Pariſhioner. And that unity of poſſeſsion doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh Tythes: <hi>Vide</hi> 30 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Dier</hi> 43. 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Br. Diſmes</hi> 17. And this Caſe of Diſmes is a parallel of the Caſe of Proxies with which in all points it doth concurre. For even as Inſtruction was the cauſe of payment of Tythes, ſo Viſitation which was alwaies accompanied with Inſtruction (<hi>Littleton ca. de Frank almoigne</hi> 30. <hi>b.</hi>) was the cauſe of <hi>Proxies:</hi> and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yths are now due, &amp; payable to Lay perſons who have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed impropriate Rectories, though they give no Inſtruction: So Proxies are due and payable to Ordinaries out of Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations and Religious Houſes diſſolved, though their Viſitation ceaſe. And as there can be no Praeſcription <hi>de non decimando,</hi> as 'tis commonly ſaid in our Books. So the Canon Law hath a Rule, <hi>Quòd nulla eſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Procurationem Praeſcriptio. Instit. juris Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicil.</hi> 2. <hi>de Cenſibus.</hi> And therefore <hi>Proxies</hi> which reſemble Tythes in other points, may well be compared to them in this
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169004:38"/>point, <hi>viz.</hi> that they ſhall not be ſubject to extinguiſhment by unity of Poſſeſsion.</p>
               <p>Thus have I imparted the whole Caſe of Proxies, which haply came into my hands after I had penned for my own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate uſe the foregoing Treatiſe, which I the rather have ſet down at large, to the end that any party grieved at this pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might (by weighing all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Caſe) either receive information for his ſatisfaction, or advantage (if there it be to be found) for his eaſe. And having thus farre forth travelled in the buſineſs, I leave both my ſelf and my labour in this particular to the charitable cenſure of the diſcreet and courteous Reader. For my part I hope there is no man ſuſpects me partiall, nor ſhall find me ſo: this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing age will ſoon diſcover ſuch a fault, and being found not ſuffer it to paſs without touch of reprehenſion. To be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, equally ballanced, inclining nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to this or that hand, but with my ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt endeavour to preſs, and facilitate the way towards Truth and Peace, was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169004:39"/>the reſolution I' brought with me when firſt I ſetled upon this argument. I ſay Truth and Peace were before mine eyes as my principall objects; which if I be not ſo happy as to find, it will excuſe that I have cordially ſought. To ſpeak it in a word; what I could gather up at the ſhoars and ſhallowes (<hi>Littus enim legi,</hi> not adventuring to launch into the Ocean) I have faithfully to my power communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted concerning the point of <hi>Procurations.</hi> And now what ſhall I more ſay? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Concil. Nicen. Can. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> let not any private ſpirit (by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch curioſity and ſtudy of Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) cauſeleſly goe about to move things well ſettled out of their ancient places, nor (without evident inconvenience diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and judged by the eye of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) ſo much as think of the word <hi>Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but let antient Cuſtomes ſtand. The wiſdome of all times giving us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand (from the nature of man ſo prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted to change) of what evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence ſuch attempt may fall out to be by the difficulty<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, c. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dar. Pyth. Od. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>112.</hi>
                  </note> that is found oftimes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169004:39"/>to follow in the reſetling of things (haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and inconſiderately diſtrubed) in their former ſtation and place. But I have done with this point, and do now deſcend to enquire after another Eccleſiaſticall pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, namely Synodals.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:169004:40"/>
            <head>De Synodalibus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as I have here ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon me to treat of this <hi>Synodal</hi> due, I think it not incongruous to ſay (however little yet) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Synod it ſelf, becauſe at that time it was uſually paid. Now of Synods there are found ſundry kinds, <hi>Occumenical, National, Provincial,</hi> and <hi>Dioceſan: Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall</hi> is a Synod out of divers Nations; <hi>National</hi> out of divers Provinces; <hi>Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> out of divers Dioceſs; <hi>Dioceſan</hi> out of one Dioceſs only. The <hi>Oecumenical</hi> and <hi>National</hi> Synods were ever aſſembled by authority Imperial, Regal, or Papal. The <hi>Provincial</hi> by Metropolitans or Patriarchs; The <hi>Dioceſan</hi> by the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169004:40"/>I recite them briefly, for to make a long Narration or Story of the manner of aſſembling, order of ſeſsion, and form of proceeding obſerved in each particular Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod were to trifle out the time, and to waſte Paper, yea overmuch to treſpaſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the patience (as I fear I have already done) of the judioious reader, eſpecially in this place, where the diſcourſe upon that ſubject can be little elſe then a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a work by the by, as we vulgarly ſay. <hi>Duarenus</hi> will briefly ſatisfie ſuch as deſire information in the point of Synods,<note place="margin">Duarenus.</note> unto whom (<hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11. of his book <hi>de ſacris Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae miniſteriis &amp; beneficiis</hi>) I referre them. This only I would intimate, and I will doe but little more then ſo (reſerving a few words for Dioceſan Synods only) how carefull and how circumſpect religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Emperors and godly Biſhops in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times have been, by the often aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of Synods and calling of Councels (the frequent celebration whereof as it was <hi>praecipua agri dominici cultura,</hi> as the Councel of <hi>Baſil</hi> expreſſeth it:<note place="margin">Conſil. Baſil Bin. to. <hi>4.</hi> ſeſſ. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> So the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169004:41"/>thereof was found to be very much diſadvantageous to it,<note place="margin">Novel. Conſt. <hi>123.</hi> ca. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> as the Emperor long before that Councell in his <hi>Novel-Conſtitutions</hi> ſeems to complain) to prevent as well the overſpreading poyſon of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy wherewith the field of the Church was in thoſe times much infeſted; as alſo to allay (as much as in them lay) ſuch tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts of contention as were oftimes ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up by ſeditious and factious ſpirits to diſturb the Common peace. The famous Oecumenical Councel of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Chalced. can. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> in the time of <hi>Martian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> Emperors, graced with an Aſſembly of 630 Biſhops, and before that a Councel at <hi>Antioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Antioch. c. <hi>20.</hi> Cmcil. Nicen. c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and before them both the Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> (all cited in the volume of the Decrees) made ſeverall Acts, That a Synod of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provincial Biſhops ſhould be celebrated in every Province twice a year (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the Apoſtles Canons too) and once of that twice (as the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councel hath it,<note place="margin">Canon. Apostolo rum, ca. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> differing in point of time from that of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch) ante dies quadrageſimae;</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. de Concil. <hi>18.</hi> Diſtinct. &amp;c. propter ibi, &amp;c. habeatur. eod.</note> yielding this for the reaſon, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169004:41"/>that all grudge and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice taken away, both Prieſt and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might offer an holy gift, and perform a pure Faſt to God. But this being found in progreſs of time a task and travell too hard for Biſhops (being for the moſt part old men) to continue, eſpecially where their Provinces were of large extent (to inſtance <hi>Germany</hi> amongſt the reſt) the cauſe alſo of ſuch frequent meetings being leſſened, time ſaw an end of that cuſtome; for neer about the middle of the 5. Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, at what time <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s Novel Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were firſt publiſhed &amp; ſent abroad. The Emperor finding a neglect of the obſervation of the double yearly Synod, commands thus (which the rather I ſet down in the very words of the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the Greek originall, for that I cannot find it in any Latin copy,<note place="margin">Novel. Juſtin. Conſtitut. <hi>123.</hi> c <hi>10.</hi> impreſs. Pariſiis <hi>1542.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gothofred</hi> or elſe) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169004:42"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſortaſſe.</note> which conſtitution of the Emperor (receiving fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrength by the ſixth General Synod,<note place="margin">Concil conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop. ca. <hi>8.</hi> Concil. Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ca. <hi>6</hi> Concil. Lateran. ca. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> held at <hi>Constantinople</hi> about the latter end of the ſixth Century: as alſo by the ſeventh General Synod celebrated at <hi>Nice</hi> about the latter end of the ſeventh Century: and long after by the Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, <hi>Anno</hi> 1215.) conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the courſe of a ſingle (not interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting or interrupting (in places where it was uſed) the cuſtome of a double) annual Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Synod for divers hundreds of years within the Empire.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dei. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> But. <hi>Quid manet ex an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquis morthus</hi> (St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> thus breaks forth) <hi>quibus</hi> Ennius <hi>dixit rem ſtare</hi> Romanam, <hi>quos ita oblivione obſoletos videmus ut non modò non colantur, ſed etiam ignorentur?</hi> So here, this Cuſtom though never ſo good, and ſo long continued, hath long ſince been buried, as it were, in oblivion, and ſo worn out of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, as that it is now as a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known (<hi>quaereliquiae? quodve vestigium?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Flor. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> as the Hiſtorian of the <hi>Veientes</hi>) and as if it
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169004:42"/>had never been. And yet not ſo as that it ſuffered utter aboliſhment: No, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Sueton. in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiano.</note> a ſhoot from the ſame root ſprung forth, and up it came againe, but ſomewhat altered from what it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: For in the Councell of <hi>Baſil</hi> (that troubleſome<note n="*" place="margin">Grantz. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xon. l. <hi>11.</hi> ca. <hi>20.</hi> Conſil. Baſil. Seſſ. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> Councell) in the time of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius</hi> the fourth, about the year 1433. it was there decreed (upon neglect, I doubt not, of the annual Provincial Synod) and an Act paſſed, that a triennial Provincal Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod ſhould thenceforth be obſerved, which if the wiſdome of thoſe times, and thence downward, had thought meet to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinned and tranſmitted to poſterity, it might have been a means of producing many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Conſtitutions, that the modern and after ages muſt be content to want and wiſh for. But bleſſed be God for thoſe we have. The preſent times doe, and muſt thankfully acknowledge the ſingular benefit they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from them, which (without queſtion) would have been enlarged and augmented, had there not been found cauſe ſufficient of a ceſſation, at leaſt of a longer inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittency
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169004:43"/>of time for their Synods then is limited in, or warranted by the Councel Act. For as when the prey is taken, the Huntſman ceaſeth to purſue; and <hi>hoſte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellato</hi> the Trumpet ſoundeth a retreat, and the Souldier returns triumphantly home. So here, the ſtormes of Hereticall fury which for a long time diſquieted the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſtate of the Church, being at the length well aſwaged, differences and diſtractions about Eccleſiaſtical affairs compoſed, and all things in ſome good ſort ſetled abroad. The Biſhops (not called upon by their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitans) repoſe themſelves within the limits of their own Dioceſes, where, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an Act made in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Baſil</hi> each Biſhop was to convocate his Clergie, and celebrate alſo a Synod in the ſame his Dioceſs at leaſt<note n="*" place="margin">C. annis ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis <hi>18.</hi> Diſtinct. Abb. in c. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querent. de of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio Ordinarii. C. Epiſcopus <hi>18.</hi> Dictinct. Concil. Baſil. Seſſ. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> once a year. In this Synod (being moſt uſually held in the Cathedrall of every Dioceſs) the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop himſelf (<hi>niſi gravi neceſsitate, vel ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonico impedimento detentus,</hi> in which caſe ſome other by delegation from him) ſate Preſident; who being there ſate, and having
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169004:43"/>his aſſembled Clergie about him, with ſuch other of the Laity whom neceſſary cauſe called thither; after earneſt invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the aſsiſtance and direction of Gods Spirit, and the further accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch accuſtomed rites as were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily requiſite and preparative to the buſineſs. The Biſhop or his Subſtitute, ſelected or called forth <hi>ſeptem è plebe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. Epiſcopus in Synodo <hi>35.</hi> q. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> ſaith the Decree, <hi>de qualibet parochia,</hi> adds the Gloſſe; <hi>Men grave, and of ripe years, fearing God, and for honeſty ſuch as were of beſt repute amongſt the people.</hi> To each of theſe men the Praeſident of the Synod delivered an Oath, the form whereof was as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>viz. Amodò in antea quicquid noſti aut au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti aut poſtmodùm inquiſiturus es quod contra Dei voluntatem &amp; rectam Chriſtianitatem in Parochia factum ſit, aut futurum erit, ſi in die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tuis evenerit, tantùm ut ad tuam cognitionem quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> modo perveniat. Si ſcis, aut tibi fue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it indicatum Synodalem cauſam eſſe &amp; ad miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Epiſcopi pertinere; quòd tu nec propter amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem nec propter timorem, nec propter pretium, nec propter parentelam ullatenus celes Epiſcopum aut
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169004:44"/>ejus miſſum cui hoc inquirere juſſe it quandocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que te ex hoc interrogaverit, Sic te Deus adjuvet, &amp; iſtae Sanctorum reliquiae.</hi> By virtue of which oath, and office thereupon depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the extent of their authority and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry ſtretcht very far, namely into all buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes cognizable, &amp; puniſhable by juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Eccleſiaſtical,<note place="margin">Conſil. Baſilienſ. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſio <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> Simony, Hereſie, Uſury, Sacriledg Sorcery, Divination, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, Superſtition, Alienation of Church Livings, Fornication, and many other things beſides. All which, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe they found to fall within the compaſs of their inquiſition (as cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired) thoſe ſeven men, called in the Law <hi>Teſtes Synodales</hi> preſented either in writing, or otherwiſe interrogated in the open Synod, delivered by way of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <hi>vivâ voce</hi> to the Biſhop or his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, which was received by Notaries then preſent appointed for that purpoſe; that accordingly things amiſs might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to reformation, and amended, the parties found remiſs might be ſtirred up to better performances, and the perſons
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169004:44"/>peccant in any ſort condignly puniſhed. And ſo ſurely they were: For albeit on the one hand there was tenderneſs uſed towards ſinne ſecretly acted, eſpecially where ſcandall might probably faſten it ſelf upon ſome eminent calling; and ſo a ſecret &amp; gentle animadverſion (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Iſocrat. Orat. <hi>2.</hi> ad Nicoc. p. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> as the Orator expreſſeth it) out of the wiſdome of the Synodicall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, was anſwerably inflicted upon the offending party (yea for ſmaller miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors,<note place="margin">Spelman. Concil. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>362.</hi>
               </note> and the firſt a pecuniary pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment was in favour impoſed) yet on the other hand, when a fault committed became ſo manifeſt, that a connivance or private ſatisfaction might cauſe a publick offence, then no interceſsion;<note place="margin">Tacit. annal. l. <hi>14.</hi> p <hi>314.</hi>
               </note> no <hi>pecunia ob delicta,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> in another caſe could exempt from cenſure and ſhame; but as the offence was manifeſt,<note place="margin">Antiquit. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. p. <hi>197.</hi> Extr. de Officio Jud. Ordinarii c. l. reſragab. § finali.</note> ſo ſhould the puniſhment be as notorious: be the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon high or low his calling could not quit him free; which if he refuſed to undergo being a Clerk, he was turned out of his Miniſtry, and deprived of his Benefice;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169004:45"/>If a Laick, he was thruſt out of the Church by Excommunication, and debarred of Chriſtian ſociety, no man ſuffered to keep him company. This was in effect (ſo I take it) the manner of holding of Synods in particular Dioceſes, at leaſt a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſome part of the form of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings and cenſures therein. At which meeting I doubt not to ſay there was a <hi>Synodale,</hi> a Cenſe, or Tribute in money payd to the Biſhop, or to ſome other to his uſe from the inferiour Clergie.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Synodale</hi> among writers is found (if I miſtake not) to yield more eſpecially a two fold ſignification: For it ſignifieth not only <hi>Conventus</hi> a meeting, as <hi>Synodus</hi> doth, but likewife the Acts of that meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Concerning the former ſignification we have an inſtance out of an Epiſtle of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Third, cited by Cardinal <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> in the 8. Tome of his Annals about the year 738. <hi>Catholica</hi> (ſaith he,<note place="margin">Baronius.</note> writng to the Biſhops of the Provinces of <hi>Bajory</hi> and <hi>Almany) Sanctorum Patrum authoritas jubet ut his in anno pro ſalute populi Christiani ſeu exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169004:45"/>adoptionis filiorum</hi> Synodalia <hi>debent ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrari, &amp;c.</hi> Here <hi>Synodale</hi> is taken for the Meeting or Synod it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Touching the latter acceptation,<note place="margin">Histor. Tripar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. l. <hi>7.</hi> ſol. <hi>452.</hi>
               </note> I find it in the Tripartite Hiſtory, where men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made of a Synod of Biſhops aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Antioch</hi> out of divers Provinces concerning the Hereſie broached by <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> and upheld by his and his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents againſt the conſubſtantiality of the Sonne of God. Which point being there diſputed by the Biſhops Orthodox &amp; He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, it was at length diſcuſſed, and this <hi>Acaſius</hi> with his Aſſociates being through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced with the evidenceof truth <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantialitatem profeſsi ſunt,</hi> ſaith the Story, they were conſtrained to give glory to God by the acknowledgement of their errors, and in ſubſcribing to the Orthodox Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and Creed of the Church: which done the Biſhops of that Synod ſent the ſame Profeſsion together with a copy of the <hi>Nccene</hi> Creed to <hi>Jovinian</hi> the Emperor, to the end the ſaid Emperor might have knowledge of their proceeding with this
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169004:46"/>
               <hi>Acaſius,</hi> and be made acquainted with the uniformity of his and his adherents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief touching that Creed. <hi>Hunc libellum</hi> (ſaith that Synod, meaning the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed) <hi>in collectione Synodalium Sabini conſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum invenimus.</hi> In this place I take <hi>Synoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> to mean the Acts of that Synod which were collected and digeſted by this <hi>Sabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. Tripar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. l. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>392.</hi>
               </note> as a little before in that Story the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may find written. So now here is <hi>Synodale,</hi> the Meeting, and <hi>Synodalia</hi> too, the Acts of the Meeting. But what's all this (will ſome ſay) to <hi>Synodale,</hi> the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being the very thing principally in purſuit of inquiſition in this place? To which I anſwer, that I have found yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Synodale,</hi> which (as I conceive) will come neer to our purpoſe, yea and muſt neceſſarily be taken for this very payment that now we are upon.</p>
            <p>In the Appendix to the 3. General <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> Councel, and in the ſecond part of that Appendix there is an Epiſtle of Pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the 3. to certain Archdeacons and Deans, reproving them for extorting of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169004:46"/>moneys from the Clergy <hi>ſub diverſis nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus</hi> in a fraudulent kind of way. <hi>Et hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi exactionem</hi> (ſaith the Pope in that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle) <hi>ut eam liberiùs videamint exigere, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doque conſuetudinem Epiſcopalem, quandoque</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodalia, <hi>quandoque Denarios Paſchales appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes.</hi> The Archdeacons and Deans the rather as it ſhould ſeem to obtain their unjuſt demands, ſhrowded them under ſuch ſpecious Titles of dues as they knew were currantly warrantable, and would not be denyed. This I take the ſenſe to be. And admit it comes not off ſo clear but that ſome dregs of prejudice in reſpect of the Exactors, might in ſome ſort ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the equity of this <hi>Synodal</hi> demand: yet this I hold to be a clear truth, that as the abuſe of a thing ought not to take away or aboliſh a neceſſary or convenient uſe; ſo neither can, or ought any unjuſt receipt impeach or make void a juſt demand: For it will be granted (I ſuppoſe) that no Archdeacon or Dean hath right of claim <hi>Jure communi Eccleſiaſtico</hi> to the <hi>Synodal</hi> pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but only by compoſition with, or
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169004:47"/>preſcription from the Biſhop: ſo that if under colour and pretence of ſuch right, the Archdeacon or Dean ſhall require <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodalia</hi> as a due by Law peculiar &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to themſelves, it may wel be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted extortion in them, which, <hi>bonâ fide,</hi> by them demanded in the right of the Biſhop, or in their own names and right by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſcribed cuſtome from the Biſhop, would be a juſt demand: ſo that hence I conclude there is <hi>Synodale</hi> a payment, and that Pope <hi>Alexanders</hi> reprehenſive Epiſtle (as to the equity of that due) to be in no particular repugnant or contradictory. But I will ſtay no longer upon this point; let the judicious Reader examine the place and ſatisfie himſelf. I proceed.</p>
            <p>This Synodal and Synodical due had antiently two other names whereby it was known and diſtinguiſhed, which time hath now worn out from common uſe: The one impoſed from the original cauſe and reaſon of the pay being <hi>ob hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Cathedrae Epiſcopalis,</hi> and ſo termed CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THEDRATICUM: The other aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169004:47"/>a name from its time of payment, and is called <hi>Synodaticum,</hi> (both one and the ſame thing, excepting the nominal diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) and ſo are they taken in the Law, being found ofttimes to go together, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the one expounding the meaning of the other. Inſtance hereof I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon in this place as a matter of principall proof, but paſs it over, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſolution and anſwers to certain queſtions following <hi>ex incidenti</hi> to ſpeak ſomething of it. The queſtions are
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>What this payment, (couched under the terms of</hi> Cathedraticum <hi>and</hi> Synodaticum) <hi>anciently was?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>The reaſon why payd.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>The time when it was firſt impoſed?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>The time when it was uſually paid?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. <hi>How, and by what Law it came to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the Church, and paid by the Clergie?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VI. and laſtly, <hi>What relative neerneſs our</hi> Synodale <hi>now hath unto this antient</hi> Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draticum?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To each of theſe queſtions a brief ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. I begin with the firſt, namely,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169004:48"/>
               <hi>What this</hi> Cathedratick <hi>payment was:</hi> and to this I anſwer; That as well by the Acts of certain Councels before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to wit <hi>Bracar</hi> and <hi>Toledo,</hi> as by the Conſtitutions and Reſcripts of Popes, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedraticum</hi> appears to be a cenſe or ſumme of money of two ſhillings payd to the Biſhop by the inferiour Clergy. <hi>Illud te volumus modis omnibus cuſtodire ne qui Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> Siciliae <hi>de Parochiis ad ſe pertinentibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Cathedratici amplius quàm duos ſolidos prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumant accipere.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. Illud. &amp;c. placuit. ibi &amp;c. inter caetera eod. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Thus Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> to <hi>Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conius</hi> the Illuſtrious: So in a difference that fell out bewteen the Biſhop of <hi>Aſciſi, (Aſsiſinatin.</hi> the Decreatals read, which <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telius</hi> from <hi>Leander</hi> gathers to be <hi>Aſsiſi,</hi> a Town within the confines of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbria</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi>) and the Governour of St. <hi>Benet</hi> not farre from thence, about Epiſcopal rights. <hi>Honorius</hi> the third,<note place="margin">Ext. de officico Judicis Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narii c. conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. &amp; Gloſſ. ibid. in v. Duos ſelidos.</note> upon complaint made unto him againſt the Biſhop, ſets down what dues and duties did of right apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto the Biſhop from the Churches and Chappels belonging unto the ſaid Monaſtery, and amongſt the reſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169004:48"/>ſeth <hi>Two ſhillings nomine Cathedratici,</hi> which is a Penſion payd to the Biſhop <hi>à qualibet Eccleſiâ ſocundum loci conſuetudinem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abb. c. conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. de officio Judicis Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii.</note> as <hi>Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitan</hi> upon the Text there. Two ſhilings then was the uſuall ſumme payd, but why payd, the reaſon is yet to render.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi> anſwers to it, and ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>II.</hi> Hoſtienſ. inſum. de Cenſibus. §. Ex quibus, ver. Cathedraticum autem.</note> that it was payd <hi>in argumentum ſubjectionis &amp; ob honorem Cathedrae;</hi> ſo he: And the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Bracar</hi> cited in the Decree, <hi>Placuit ut nullus Epiſcoporum per ſuas Dioeceſes ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans praeter honorem Cathedrae ſuae, id eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit.</note> 
               <hi>Duos ſolidos, aliud aliquid per Eccleſias tollat.</hi> Thus there; for honour then of the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Chair, and in token and argument of ſubjection to the Biſhop was this ſum anciently payd: And no marvel if we rightly weigh the dignity of his perſon, the amplitude of his power, and the great authority that he had in former dayes: For conſidered firſt <hi>jure ordinis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ext. de Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Domibus c. Conſtitutos.</note> he had the Ordination of Clerks, Conſecration of Altars and Churches with ſuch like Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives. Secondly conſidered <hi>reſpectu</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> in caſu.</note> 
               <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictionis;</hi> and ſo he had the power of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169004:49"/>correcting and excommunicating, yea unto him belonged Inſtitution and Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Clerks: in a word, the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of all cauſes by Law appertaining <hi>ad forum Eccleſiaſticum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ext. de Officio Judicis O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii c. Conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</note> Laſtly conſidered, with reſpect to the power that he had <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Dioeceſana,</hi> as he was the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> in caſa.</note> Dioeceſan; and ſo he had <hi>Jus Cenſus &amp; Cathedraticum exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> to leave other Priviledges unnamed, and <hi>Jus imponendi</hi> too, as<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſtienſ. de cenſibus. §. Quis imponere poteſt. Duaren. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris Eccl. mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steriis &amp; b ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiis l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi> adds, which ſhews that the Biſhop in time paſt was (to ſay no more) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But <hi>Duare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> explains the reaſon of this payment a little further; for thus he writes: <hi>Dicitur hoc jus vulgo Cathedraticum, quod Cathedrae, id eſt, honori Epiſcopali debeatur. Cathedra enim in jure Pontificio pro honore, ac munere Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſaepe accipitur, propterea quòd olim Epiſcopi quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum munus prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ium ac praecipium eſt docere, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in ſolio, &amp; Cathedra docebant.</hi> Thus he, which ſhall be the cloſe of my anſwer to the ſecond queſtion. The third follows, to wit, <hi>The time when is was firſt impoſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this queſtion I bring <hi>Duarenus</hi> again,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> whoſe words I will here ſet down. <hi>Post<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:169004:49"/>(ſaith he) <hi>reditus Eccleſiae (qui antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùs erant communes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duaren. ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra &amp; l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ab Epiſcopo diſtribue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur diviſi erant, &amp; ſingulis ministerits at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributi: Epiſcopis ſingulis vectigal quoddam ab inferiorbus Eccleſiis pendi coeptum est. Hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi imprimis illud eſt quod in Synodo à ſingulis Curionibus &amp; inferiarum Eccleſiarum Guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoribus exigunt. Nam duos ſolidos ſinguli Epiſcopo dare jubentur.</hi> This is plain for the time; I ſay plain ſo farre forth as it relates to, and points upon an act or buſineſs done of remarkable obſervation. It was when the Revenues of the Church came to be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (this was the Act) and allotted to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Miniſteries, then began this <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dratick</hi> payment to the Biſhop from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficed Clorgie within his Dioeceſs; even then ſaith <hi>Duarenus.</hi> And it may ſeem not unlikely that this Diviſion of the Church revenues here ſpoken of, and the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment of Paroecial bounds were in time not farre aſunder: which if ſo, the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of this <hi>Cathedratick</hi> impoſition may ſomewhat neerly be gueſſed at. For as touching the diſtinguiſhment of Pariſhes,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169004:50"/>it is evident in Story, that <hi>Euariſtus</hi> the Pope, otherwiſe called <hi>Anacletus Gracus,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 110. entred firſt upon that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; <hi>Et titulos urbis Praesbyteris diviſit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Volateran.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Volateran. l. <hi>22.</hi> Anaſtaſ. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blioth.</note> He aſſigned certain Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſet apart and conſecrated for divine worſhip (wherein the Chriſtians of theſe times as a diſtinct Congregation were wont to meet) to the Prieſts of the City to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their miniſterie in;<note place="margin">Baron. annal. ad ann <hi>112.</hi> nu. <hi>4, 5, 6.</hi>
               </note> I ſay certain Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yea, and ſometimes alſo <hi>Delubra Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilium,</hi> the very Paganiſh Temples too were by Imperiall Edict and Deſtination manci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated to ſuch religious ſervices. But I doubt whether I may adventure the found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this <hi>Cathedratick</hi> payment ſo high as this particular act of diſtinguiſhment by <hi>Euariſtus,</hi> being only bounded within the City. It may be conceived rather to acquire its being by occaſion of ſome more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall act of the ſame nature in the time of the Churches better reſt, for now it was under perſecution, and no time then for ſuch ſetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Church indeed was now (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in <hi>Trajans</hi> time, otherwiſe ſo good an
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169004:50"/>Emperor) in much diſtreſs, perſecution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot and preſſing: And yet Chriſtianity (ſuch is the nature of Gods ſeed) was ſtill<note n="*" place="margin">Neque enim Civitates tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm ſed vicos a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que etiam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os ſuperctitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtius conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio perv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gata est. <hi>Plin. l. 10. Ep. 97.</hi>
               </note> growing, inſomuch that the Pagauiſh Temples in ſome places of the Empire were left almoſt unfrequented, as <hi>Pliny</hi> notes in an Epiſtle of his to <hi>Trajan;</hi> yea, and ſo great were the numbers of Chriſtians in <hi>Bythinia,</hi> that, as the ſame <hi>Pliny</hi> confeſſeth (being <hi>Ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jans</hi> Lieutenant<note n="*">Cum <hi>Hiſpaniarum</hi> Praeſecturam gorere] ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> annotat <hi>Funccius</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> Commentariorum in Chronologiam ſuam ad annum <hi>110.</hi> Et innuit i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Author hanc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtulam <hi>Plinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ex <hi>Hiſpania</hi> ſuiſſe ſcriptam. Sed <hi>Plinium Hiſpaniarum</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecturam geſſiſſe, nuſquam apud proba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, Authore, praet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>Fanccium</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>torem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lioqui ſatis oculotum &amp; perspica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m) memini me legiſſe. Proconſulatum in <hi>Bythi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia</hi> ſe eoer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuiſſe ex Epiſt. <hi>Plin.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>28.</hi> Et ejuſdem vitâ operi ſuo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixâ per <hi>Catanaeum</hi> hand diffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le eſt colligere. Et inde hane ſuam <hi>97.</hi> Epiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ad <hi>Trajanum</hi> tranſm ſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Author eſt Chron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>graphorum ſui temporis (quos equidem vidi) ſacile princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, doctiſſimus <hi>Sethus Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> there) that they had well nigh ſpoiled the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans market, <hi>Victimarum ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus emptor,</hi> ſaith he. Perſecution did nothing at all advance their cauſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Goſpel got ground of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, and though fire and ſword oppoſed, the people would after Chriſt by any means. Thus, as alſo by ſuch poor Priviledges of liberty, as the Chriſtians could obtain by Imperiall diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (being but few and narrowly confined for the moſt part) they multiplied apace. Nor yet were thoſe Priviledges conſtant
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169004:51"/>and continuing. But even as it is with the Moon, that ſometime is in the Wax and ſometimes in the Wane; ſo was it with the Church in theſe times; one while under Lee ſheltered from the tempeſts of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh immanity, a while after expoſed to the whirlewind of tyrannicall rage. What the favour of one Emperor built up, the fury of another pulled down: And thus was it with the Church from <hi>Nero,</hi> (in whoſe time Satan being enraged againſt the Woman,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel. 12.13.</hi> Sucton in vita Neron. pa. <hi>148.</hi> Sect. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> the firſt of the Ten bloody perſecutions began) till <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, during which time I ſeek not for the ſetling, nor read not of the mentioning of this Cenſe. Albeit I find toward the latter end of <hi>Galtenus</hi> his reign, about the year 260. and ſomewhat above 40 years before <hi>Constantine,</hi> that the work of diſtinguiſhing Paroecial Limits was then undertaken again by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Pope, who laying hold upon the opportunity of a favourable I dict of <hi>Galienus</hi> (affrighted, and forced to remorſe toward the Chriſtians by many prodigious tokens of Gods apparent indignation) and beginning in the City of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169004:51"/>
               <hi>Rome,</hi> where his Predeceſſor <hi>Euariſtus</hi> left, he again divided, reduced, and ſetled what by reaſon of perſecution lay confuſedly waſte, aſsigning to the ſeverall Pariſhes,<note place="margin">Baron. annal. ad a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. <hi>270.</hi> n. <hi>17.</hi> lege et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am notas ad S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xtum tom. <hi>1.</hi> Concil Bin. edit. pa. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> by him diſtinguiſhed, ſeverall Prieſts to inſtruct the people, and to each Church its <hi>Coemiterium;</hi> yea, moreover <hi>Paroclias &amp; Dioeceſes fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s diſtribuit quo quiſque finibus limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuis contentus eſſet, as Funccius</hi> out of the Decree hath collected.<note place="margin">Func. Comment. in Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enniog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am ſuam ad an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>68 13.</hi> q <hi>1</hi> c. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias ſingulas.</note> Thus proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with endeavor to accompliſh abroad alſo what <hi>Euariſtus</hi> had but only began at home: but death or other impediments preventing, that buſineſs, was left in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places uneffected, as a work for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity to finiſh and complete. To make the matter ſhort: the work con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the diſtinguiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of Paroec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all bounds, being thus farre forth carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long (and all happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nning in the time of perſecution, or rather when the Church enjoyed its <hi>Lucida intervalla,</hi> and had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed ſome Halcyon dayes) <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, about the beginning of the 4. Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, took upon him the Government of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169004:52"/>the Imperiall Scepter, ſtayed the then Perſecution, ſhut up the dores of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Temples, and reſtored peace to the Church, and liberty to the Chriſtians; yea, and Councels (few before that time) then began to be riſe abroad.<note place="margin">Parochiall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribut on in <hi>England</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erformed by <hi>Theodorus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 668. <hi>Spelin. Concil.</hi> 152. But <hi>Speed</hi> ſaith by <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius the</hi> 5. Archbiſhop al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of <hi>Canter.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 636.</note> About this time it may be ſuppoſed that the diviſion of Church revenues ſpoken of by <hi>Duare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> was made, and this Cenſe then fixed. Though I confeſſe as yet I have not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it mentioned before the ſecond Councel of <hi>Bracar,</hi> held a little after the middle of the 5. Century, about the year 570. which Councel I find doth only li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, not conſtitute this payment, and therefore it muſt be ſought for a little higher, wherein I crave the Readers pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for a further inquiſition. And ſo I paſs away to the 4. Queſtion, namely?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When this Cenſe or Penſion was uſually paid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I find to be,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> as before is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned moſt uſually <hi>in Synodo;</hi> and that therefore it was called <hi>Synodaticum, quia in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169004:52"/>Synodo frequentius dabatur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hoſtienſis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hostienſ in ſum de Cenſihus. §. Ex qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus.</note> I ſay it was uſually but not alwayes ſo paid: For in the Decretals there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what that ſeems to oppoſe the limitation and reſtriction of this payment to <hi>Synodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Meetings only.<note place="margin">Extra de Cenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus c. Olim.</note> The paſſage there is this: There aroſe a queſtion about the payment of this <hi>Synodaticum,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Suit between a Biſhop of <hi>Spoleto</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> and certain Clerks <hi>Plebis Rupinae</hi> within his Dioeceſs: The Biſhop requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Tres denarios Papienſes,</hi> which according to an ancient Cuſtome, the Clergy were wont to pay at the Feaſts of the Nativity and Eaſter, to wit, at each Feaſt ſo much pro <hi>Synodatico.</hi> Now the ſaid Clerks or Clergy having for thirty ſix years altered their payment, and rendring to the Biſhop and his Predeceſſors for ſo long time only <hi>Tres denarios Lucenſes</hi> at each Feaſt, being a kind of money of farre leſs value then the former) endeavoured to preſcribe againſt the Biſhop, who thought himſelf ſafe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to avoid the danger of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription by receiving of it <hi>ſub proteſtatione,</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:169004:53"/>and that in ſo doing his right could not be impeached, wherein he had like to have been deceived. A great deal of adoe there was, and much bickering between the Biſhop and his Clergy, and at length the matter was brought to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third to be decided, who examining the cauſe, and finding the preſcription of the defendant parties to be only four years ſhort of a full preſcription,<note place="margin">Quadragenalis praeſiriptio tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit omnem actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Ext. de verb. ſigniſicat. c. Cum inter, ver. per <hi>40</hi> annos.</note> namely of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years (to which time, if the Defendants could have brought their preſcription, the Biſhop had been gone notwithſtanding his proteſtation) and having alſo the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants and their Advocates anſwer, <hi>non revocatum,</hi> that <hi>Papienſis moneta</hi> was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid: The Pope thereupon paſſeth a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive ſentence for the Plaintiffe Biſhop againſt the Defendant Clergy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns them <hi>ad ſolutionem Dena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iorum Bapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſium:</hi> thus there. So that hence it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently evident, that albeit the <hi>Synodatick</hi> payment receive its denomination <hi>à Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> as being the uſual time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts payment, yet under the ſame name it was alſo payd
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169004:53"/>
               <hi>extra Synodum</hi> (namely at the Feaſts of the Nativity and Eaſter) I will not affirm <hi>abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ratione Synodi;</hi> for that before this time Synods, I mean Provincial and Dioeceſan afterwards I doubt not, were held (occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion requiring) twice a year, correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent whereunto by prevalency of cuſtome the Synodatick payment might either be doubled (which is leſs probable) or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided (which I rather incline to think, for ſo I find the ancient courſe to be in the Dioeceſs of <hi>Glouceſter</hi>) namely the payment to be divided into <hi>Synodalia Aeſtivalia, &amp; Hiemalia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Extat. in quâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam vetuſtiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma membranulâ quam penes me habeo.</note> Nor do I think that this <hi>Synoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> payment (taken to be the ſame with the <hi>Cathedratick,</hi> as I doe here and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where) was conſtantly at all times paid either <hi>in Synodo,</hi> or at the two Feaſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-named.: For it was ſometimes, and very anciently paid alſo at Viſitations. I referre the Reader to the ſeventh Councel at <hi>Toledo</hi> mentioned in the Decree,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caetera, &amp; Caſus ibi.</note> where he ſhall find a Canon againſt the exacting of more money then <hi>Two ſhillings</hi> only <hi>pro Cathedraticò</hi> in Epiſcopall viſitations.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169004:54"/>And ſo have I done with this Queſtion, and paſs to the fifth, and that is</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How, and by what Law this</hi> Cathedraticum <hi>came at the firſt to be impoſed upon the Church, and path by the Clergie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Queſtion <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi> makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> and ſaith, that it was impoſed <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate Epiſcopi,</hi> by the authority of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, within the ſphere of whoſe <hi>Quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> activity the Lawyers have found a power to move,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. per Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celot. ſuper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. juris Canon. De immunitate Eccleſ.</note> which they call <hi>Lex Dioe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſana;</hi> a term by them invented (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not explicitely found in any Text in Law) for the clear and diſtinctive expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Epiſcopall power in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as the ſame relates to other Lawes and Priviledges annexed to, and inherent in the Office of the Biſhop, to wit, <hi>Lex juriſdictionis, &amp; Jus ordinis.</hi> And therfore it is that <hi>Panormitan</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Abb. in ca. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. de Offic. Jud. Ordinar. ubi plura de le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege Dioeceſ.</note> that they are <hi>vocabula Magiſtralia magis quàm juris.</hi> But to ſtand no longer upon the term. Thus much I find that this part of Epiſcopall power thus
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169004:54"/>diſtinguiſhed and actuated by this Law, did formerly yield the Biſhop a large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of command over all the Churches and Clergy within his Dioeceſs; all, I ſay, none<note n="*" place="margin">Gloſſ. in ver. Epiſcopus c. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, Dist. <hi>18.</hi> Ext. de Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. &amp; obed. c. <hi>9.</hi> Quod ſuper &amp; gloſſ. ibi in ver. Dioeceſana.</note> excepted but the Ciſtertians, who by virtue of their order had ſome Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of immunity more then ordinary, as namely to be abſent from <hi>Synodicall</hi> Meetings aſſembled by the Biſhop within his Dioeceſs, and from payments then made to him by the other Clergy with ſuch like. This then was the Law, and by virtue of this Law founded in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop (or power ſettled upon him by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial donation or diſpenſation) this Cenſe was by him<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>10</hi> qu. <hi>1.</hi> in. Caſu.</note> received, and the payment thereof fixed, and impoſed upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Clergy, which now is become a charge perpetuall annexed to their Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and thence annually to be payd (if greater authority interrupt not the ancient courſe) as an <hi>Onus Eccleſiaſticum</hi> a Church burden or charge: yea, and to ſhew that it is no ſtrange and unheard of burden no innovated payment. It is ſaid to be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169004:55"/>(beſides its impoſition by Law) <hi>Onus Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narium.</hi> The Gloſs upon the Provincial Conſtitutions <hi>de officio Vicarii</hi> makes it good,<note place="margin">C. Quoniam in ver. Onera Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica.</note> where the Reader may find thoſe words. <hi>Solutio Cathedratici, Synodatici &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curationum ratione viſitationis, &amp; alia hujuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di de quibus non dubitatur quin ſunt onera ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſuum capiunt effectum ab impoſitione legis.</hi> But this place of <hi>Lyndewoods</hi> Gloſſe gives occaſion to a queſtion namely, Whether Procurations be impoſed and due by the ſame Law that <hi>Cathedratica</hi> are: To which I anſwer, that (queſtionleſſe) they are not. For <hi>Cathedraticum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> in caſu.</note> 
               <hi>Synodaticum, tertia vel quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta pars Decimationum &amp; Oblationum, &amp;c.</hi> are <hi>Cenſus,</hi> and exacted or impoſed as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Lege Dioeceſanâ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſ. in v. Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Ext. de Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus, c. Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus.</note> But <hi>Procuratio</hi> is not properly <hi>Cenſus,</hi> but <hi>Penſio.</hi> And as it is ſo, and reduced to a certainty of ſumme, that Penſion hath its ground, as before intimated from Papal Conſtitution, and that Conſtitution alſo its root and footing from a principle in the very Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And ſo much <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi> is bold to aſſert, when ſpeaking of <hi>Procuratio</hi> as it is
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169004:55"/>due <hi>ratione viſitationis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſt. ubi ſupra. § A quibus danda ſit.</note> he ſaith that it is <hi>Adeò debita quod quamvis nullas expenſas faciat Epiſcopus propter viſitationem nihilominus eam recipit.</hi> And the reaſon he urgeth is out of St <hi>Paul,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> out of the Law of Nature; <hi>Qui ſeminat ſpiritualia metere debeat carnalia.</hi> Thus <hi>Hoſtienſis,</hi> who propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle in bare poſitive terms, doth not ſo fully (as I conjecture) preſs the duty and ſcope of the Text: For theſe are the words;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>If we have ſown unto you ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>is it a great thing if we reap your carnall?</hi> The Interrogation ſeeming vehemently to inforce a redition or retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution on the one hand, eſpecially upon the performance of the conditional pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on the other: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as much to ſay, Is it a great thing? No, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the duty, the charge is not worth naming. But this is an excurſion, I return. We ſee the Law, that is to ſay, the Law Dioeceſan carries the authority of this <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedratick</hi> impoſition, which therefore is ſaid to be <hi>Epiſcopale,</hi> becauſe founded ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally in, or ſettled ſolely upon the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169004:56"/>to whom <hi>in honorem Cathedrae,</hi> and in token of ſubjection and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuperiority to him, as before is expreſſed, it was by the Clergie anciently rendred, and may now by him be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exacted from them, as I conceive. And this is my anſwer to the fifth Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. The ſixth and laſt is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What relative nearneſs our</hi> Synodale <hi>now hath unto this ancient</hi> Cathedraticum.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer in a word,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> That albeit to <hi>Cathedraticum</hi> our <hi>Synodale</hi> ſeems to have but ſmall or no relation, becauſe they ſo much differ in literall enunciation, yet not ſo to <hi>Synodaticum;</hi> to which both in ſenſe, ſignification, and literall likeneſs it doth very ſtrongly referre. That being a payment of <hi>Two ſhillings;</hi> ours for the moſt part the ſame: that paid moſt uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at <hi>Synodicall</hi> Meetings, and anciently ſometimes at Viſitations; our <hi>Synodale</hi> (ſince Synods diſcontinued) payd at Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations altogether, at leaſt in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169004:56"/>ſo. Take them then, and wynd them up in one clue or bottom, and all of them make (as I conceive) but one payment. One I ſay, and that very identicall one, that now is in uſe of receipt in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, known and diſtinguiſhed by the name <hi>Synodale,</hi> or the <hi>Synodal</hi> payment,<note place="margin">Raſtal. tit. Penſions, &amp;c.</note> or (which is the ſame) the <hi>Synody.</hi> The <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nody</hi> I ſay, which by Act of Parliament of 34 <hi>H.</hi> 8. is reckoned as a Church due; for the recovery whereof in caſe of denyall, a ſufficient proviſion is by that Act made: And upon great reaſon too, for that the ſaid <hi>Synody,</hi> or <hi>Synodal</hi> being a Penſion cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, is valued in the Kings Books, and his Majeſty receiveth an yearly Tenth out of it. And this is all that for the preſent I have to ſay touching this <hi>Synodale:</hi> In which diſcourſe if I have erred, I humbly implore the charitable cenſure of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Reader, <hi>&amp;</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—praebeat <hi>Alcinoi</hi> poma benignus ager.</q>
            <p>Let others better ſtudied this way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169004:57"/>or ſuffer with patieene till time and further induſtry ſhall diſcover to me my miſtakings, which if haply once I finde, I ſhall haſtily retract. In the mean time I leave the point, as now it ſtands, and paſſe unto another Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall due, namely <hi>Pentecoſtalls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:169004:57"/>
            <head>De Pentecoſtalibus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S he that travels in a miſt, or in parts unknown calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every one he meets with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for direction; and as he that ſeeks paſſage through a dark room catcheth at every hand that may lead him to the light; ſo am I conſtrained to doe in the diſquiſition and ſearch after this ancient Church-due, <hi>Pentecoſtals.</hi> For the Canon Law, and Provincial Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo much as I have read, they make no mention of them under this Title. I have heard ſome roave at them (as he in the holy Story that drew his bow <hi>in incertum</hi>) &amp; to ſay,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 22.34.</note> that ſurely they were thoſe <hi>Peter-pence</hi> anciently ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> out of this Land,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169004:58"/>and continued to the Church unto this day under another name, and I know not what. But <hi>Peter-pence</hi> they cannot be; for if we examine the antiquity of the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, ſo farre as I can diſcern, we ſhall finde a great deal of difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. It is certain (for ought that ever I have read or heard to the contrary) that untill the time of <hi>Ina,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Polyd. Virgil. Aug. Hiſt l. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>89.</hi> &amp; <hi>90.</hi>
               </note> King of the Weſt-Saxons, who lived about nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years agoe, <hi>Peter-pence</hi> were never heard of in this Land; but our <hi>Pentecostal</hi> (if I may have liberty to conjecture) was in uſe ſome hundred years before that time. Again, if we conſider the manner of their collection and payment,<note place="margin">Polyd. ubi ſupra p. <hi>90.</hi>
               </note> it was (ſaith <hi>Polydor Virgil,</hi> who was Collector of them in this Kingdome) <hi>domesticatam,</hi> from every houſe a penny; I ſay, every houſe that had but five groats worth of living Cattel,<note place="margin">Stow in annal. Edvard. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> of one manner of Cattel; as <hi>Stow:</hi> But 30. <hi>denariatus vivae pecuniae in domo ſuâ de ſuo proprio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lambard. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. Edv. Regis fol. <hi>128.</hi>
               </note> belonging unto it, as by (the Laws of King <hi>Edward</hi> before the Conqueſt) may appear. In our <hi>Pentecoſtal</hi> no ſuch matter.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169004:58"/>Laſtly (if I may not be thought <hi>nugas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere</hi>) there is yet another difference, and that is in the time of payment: for <hi>Peter-pence</hi> were uſually payd either at the Feaſt of the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lege Polyd. ubi ſupra.</note> or <hi>ad feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem quae dicitur ad vineula,</hi> commonly called <hi>Lammas</hi> day. <hi>Pentecostals</hi> ſeem to be paid upon, or about the time that doth chiefly denominate the pay, namely <hi>Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt.</hi> But that they have no relation the one to the other; yea, that <hi>Peter-pence</hi> are not <hi>in rerum natura</hi> at this time, it is evident: For that by a Statute made in the 25 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. and revived upon a Repeal 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. thoſe <hi>Peter-pence</hi> amongſt other Papall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions had their doom, and ſuffered deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved extinction by Act of Parliament. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, I ſay, albeit the Cardinal is pleaſed over haſtily, and thanks be to God, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly to collect, that a judgement fell upon this Land, when firſt it fell off from <hi>Rome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot</hi> pay.<note place="margin">Baron annal. ad an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Chr. <hi>740.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mirandum illud accidit ubi ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit pendi</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>No Vectigal, but</hi> Eleemoſyna mera. Elienſ. ad bellarm. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. responſ. p. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vectigal iſtud utcunque malè redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Haereſium allu vinne Anglicana Eccleſia ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorbetur,</hi> ſaith the Cardinal. But to leave
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169004:59"/>excurſions, and to come home unto our buſineſs, this <hi>Pentecoſtal</hi> payment ſeems (to me it doth) to be (at leaſt in the nature thereof to have reference to) an Oblation; which amongſt the Chriſtians in the elder times of the Church was moſt frequent, and yielded much in matter of yearly reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to it; devotion carrying in with a full hand what might well be ſpared to holy uſes,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> and ſpurring on the people <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (to uſe the Apoſtles phraſe) even beyond their power to munificency, as conceiving the Churches Cheſt to be the ſafeſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury. When the Tabernacle of old was to be built, ſee, the people came on to the work with ſuch zeal,<note place="margin">Exod. 36.6.</note> that <hi>Moſes</hi> was fain to proclaim a <hi>Sufficit,</hi> before the people would leave off to offer. So in the Acts of the Apoſtles we find what the Chriſtians in thoſe times did, they even ſold their poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,<note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> and left them at the Apoſtles feet. And the manner in ſucceeding times of the ancient Chriſtians alſo was, they offered not the price,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>12.</hi> q. <hi>1. c.</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes autem.</note> but even their Fields and Farms <hi>Matricibus Eccleſiis,</hi> from whence they
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169004:59"/>only received livelyhood, and left the reſt to be imployed to ſacred uſes. To Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Et nimio plus obtulerunt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores nostri nec ullum ſibi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> statuer u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vel finem Monaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteria donis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulandi. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſ. ad Apolog. reſponſ.</note> Churches nothing was thought too much, nothing too good to be offered; ſuch was the devotion of our Anceſtors. And that works of mercy and charity were eternall, and that there could not be any deed more beneficiall to the ſoul, more meritorious, then bounty to the Church; this was their perſwaſion. So that as all rivers haſten into the Sea,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note> as the Wiſe-man ſpeaks, ſo all went to the Church; yea there ſeemed to be a kind of pious contention in the people (<hi>Certatim Eccleſiae populus offerebat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duaren. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris Eccl. mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriis &amp; Benef. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Duarenus</hi>) who ſhould be firſt to bring in their offerings to this ſacred <hi>Gazophylacium:</hi> even Kings and the Great-ones of the world, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the common people brought in liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this way. Of <hi>Ethelwulphus</hi> King of the Weſt-Saxons it is thus written, that he gave the Tenth of his Kingdome free from all tributary charge to the Church.<note place="margin">Antiquit. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, pa. <hi>73.</hi>
               </note> And how liberall his Succeſſors divers of them were, till the exorbitant exceſs, and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169004:60"/>inordinate luxurious living of the Monks in this Kingdome, accompanied with the extreme neglect of Religion, did abate the edge of their dovotion, may be ſeen,<note place="margin">Antiquit. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. p. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> as in an Oration that King <hi>Edgar</hi> delivered in much paſsion &amp; grief for ſuch abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to <hi>Dunſtan</hi> then Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mecum obſecro animadvertat hic Lector ſi velit ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia apertiùs intelligere, cujus devotionis ac regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris obſervantiae ſuerunt ab antiquo <hi>Winchelcumbienſes</hi> Monachi, quando ob corum vitae ſanctitatem, integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatemque quotquot ſere in circuitu noſtro ruri manebant, aliquam portionem de ſuis frugibus &amp; terrae naſcentiis ſibi à Deo co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceſſis Eccleſiae nostrae quotannis in Elee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſynam offerendum voverunt. Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um quorum in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ tantae dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tionis Cenſus ſive redditus primò negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus ſit, aut cur illud revocaverint, ſeu amplius non ſolve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, haud uſpia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mihi conſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e potuit. Arbitror ſaue, quod poſtquam in coeperit fervor religionis atque devotionis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud ipſos <hi>Winchelcumbienſes</hi> torpere atq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſrigeſcere ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut accidit (uti reo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) tempo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Willielmi</hi> de <hi>Shcurburnia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Roberti</hi> de <hi>Upwella,</hi> o'im noſtri loci Abbatum. Tepuit etiam erga cos aliorum Christianorum devotio. Illius igitur rei ob illud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mini ut poſteri videant quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum damnum &amp; jacturam rerum juſlo Dei judicio in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nostris temporalibus tunc paſſi ſumus quando incoepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus remiſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es eſſe erga ſacram obſervantiam regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. Simulque &amp; nobis timendum ne majora mala ſint futura ſi (q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od abſit) in talem remiſſionem aliquam reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daverimus. Eam quoque ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em ſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a vivendum, ita elabo andum ut novo devotion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſpiritu concepto, ob vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ipſorum <hi>Winchelcumbienſium</hi> ſanctitatem &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud eos obſervantiam regularem corum predia ac poſſeſſiones oblationeſque angeri potiùs quàm diminui de caterò mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antur. Quae autem erat illa Oblatio ſeu Eleemoſyna le <hi>Church-ſeal</hi> oli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n nuncupata ſequens li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera de clarabit, &amp;c.—<hi>Lieger book of Winchcomb. fol. 43.</hi>
               </note> ſo alſo by a digreſsive ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſion that I find in an ancient Manuſcript con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of <hi>Winch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe,</hi> and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Occurrents and Acts of that Abby for divers hundred of years, wherin the ſtate of the Abby is much deplored in reſpect of the irregularity of the Regulars there. This
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169004:60"/>at home; and to look a little abroad, it is recorded of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, that he offered whole <hi>Saxony,</hi> that he ſubdued,<note place="margin">Baron annal. ad ann. Chr. <hi>804.</hi>
               </note> to St. <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and twelve hundred pounds yearly he brought in elſewhere <hi>ad ſervitium Apoſtolicae ſedis,</hi> beſides what he bequeathed at his death to the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Biſhops for Church and Poor,<note place="margin">Regiſtr. Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum in vit. Caroli magn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> being two parts of his goods, if <hi>Regiſtrum Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicor.</hi> report truth. And what <hi>Licinia,</hi> a very rich and wealthy Matron in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive time did, the Tripartite Story tels us,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Tripar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> that ſhe gave all her goods to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> This in foraign parts, and to go no further.<note place="margin">Can. Apoſtol ca. <hi>40.</hi> &amp; ca. <hi>41. 12.</hi> q. <hi>1</hi> c. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes &amp;c. Praecip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus, Et c. Epiſcopus, &amp; q. <hi>2.</hi> c. Vobis <hi>10</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Quae cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> reſ.</note> Now all theſe Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Biſhops after the Apoſtles times had <hi>ſub clave poteſtatis</hi> to diſpoſe of, they being thought the fitteſt inſtruments to be intruſted with the goods of the Church, to whom the charge of the ſouls of Gods people was chiefly committed. And into<note n="*" place="margin">Can. Apost. ca. <hi>40.</hi> Beda Eccl. Hiſt. Angl. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> four parts or Canonicall portions they commonly were (by Deacons firſt under the Biſhop in imitation of Apoſtolical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and afterwards by a Clergie
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169004:61"/>Steward, called in the Law<note n="a" place="margin">Diſtinct. <hi>89.</hi> c. quia in qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſdam. <hi>16</hi> q. <hi>7.</hi> c. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam in &amp;c. In nova. E. Concil. Chalced. ca <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>conomus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accomptable to the Biſhop) divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and accordingly diſtributed one part to the Prieſt or Clerks that did ſervice in the Church to which their offerings were brought. A ſecond part to the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>A</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. Schol. in Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Hiſunt Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſau <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Eccleſiae, &amp; verè. Theſauri in quibus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, inquibus Chriſti fides eſt. Dict. S. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntii Martyris de pauperibus ex Ambroſ. l. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Offic. c. <hi>28.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. <hi>82</hi> in Princip. c. Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus. Duaren l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi> de ſacris Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. miniſteriis &amp; benef. <hi>12.</hi> q. c. <hi>1.</hi> Praecipimus.</note> Poor, who were in the Primitive times called the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uches Treaſure, and of whom the Biſhops had an eſpeciall charge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. A third towards the Fabrick or repair of the Church. And the fourth and laſt part the Biſhop did uſually aſſume unto himſelf <hi>hoſpitalitatis exercendae cauſâ,</hi> and ſometimes a third part too, which when he took, he alſo undertook the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair of the Church,<note n="c" place="margin">Gloſſ. in ver. Tertius <hi>10</hi> q <hi>3.</hi> c. u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io. <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. De bis &amp;c. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quos Canones.</note> 
               <hi>Onus fabricae;</hi> ſo the Gloſs, which otherwiſe reſted upon the Prieſt or Clerks of that Church to do from the allotted divident. By this means, I mean of munificent offerings, and from Altaragies, that is, offerings made upon the altar (whereof the Biſhop had ſometimes a third part, and ſometimes a moity) as likewiſe from Oblations brought unto the Sepulchres and Shrines of Martyrs, with
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169004:61"/>ſuch like in-comes; the Church doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs became at length wonderfully enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for even the veſſels that they uſed in their Temples in ancient and aftertimes,<note place="margin">Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. l. <hi>1.</hi> ad Parmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anum. Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt. Epiſt. Epiſt. <hi>165.</hi>
               </note> being in great abundance (beſides orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherewithall they were plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtored) were of gold and ſilver: yea, and it is not improbable to conjecture that many goodly Temples whoſe curious work and coſtly materials doe yet after ſo many ages paſt give cauſe of admiration to the beholders, were even hence raiſed from the duſt, and divers Monaſteries, Priories, Religious Houſes and Hoſpitals were by this means founded and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully endowed. But to leave to ſpeak too much of that, that hath ſo long agoe for the moſt part left the world, namely libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall devotion towards the Church. In this little <hi>Pentecostale</hi> there is ſomewhat that tends that way, if the original thereof could be exactly found out. In ancient time the Biſhop was to viſit <hi>Eccleſiatim,</hi> as before is mentioned. When he came to viſit, his manner was to celebrate the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169004:62"/>Maſſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Novel. Juſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Constit. <hi>123.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> as the Emperor phraſeth it) in the Church that he viſited, which he did by his Epiſcopall authority, every Pariſh within his Dioeceſs, being <hi>Paroechia ſua;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ext. de Rap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ribus c. de ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> &amp; therfore is the whole Dioe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in reſpect of the Biſhop by the Law called <hi>Paroechia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. Quia &amp; Duarenus paſſim.</note> as likewiſe the whole Kingdome (the Province at leaſt) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> is ſo called.<note place="margin">Antiquit. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. pa. <hi>28.</hi> &amp; pa. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> 
               <note place="margin">Lyndewood Duarenus.</note> At this Maſſe the people made an offering to the Biſhop (as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times their manner was to doe to the Curate when he ſaid Maſſe on Sundayes and Holydayes) which he received. But upon this Cuſtome I cannot fix the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of this due, foraſmuch as the act of Maſsing <hi>quolibet die dominico</hi> being too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in circumſtance of time (to which our Oblation or Pentecoſtal hath ſpecial reference) doth not fitly denominate the pay. Now as all Offerings were uſually divided into four parts,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in v. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio de jureju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancto c. Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri.</note> as before is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ſo the Gloſſe upon the Provinciall Conſtitutions obſerves a fourfold cauſe or reaſon for which the people in ancient
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169004:62"/>times were bound to bring their Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Church: As namely firſt <hi>ex praecedenti Conventione;</hi> a mans houſe or land being tied by a preceding contract for a certain Oblation to be made at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time or times.<note place="margin">Ext. de verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſignificat. c. Cum inter in Rubrica <hi>12.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. videntes lege Levitic. <hi>27.</hi> v. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> Which kind of Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, albeit it be of the nature of a Cenſe or Impoſition, becauſe it proceeds <hi>è con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractu,</hi> yet being a thing ſettled upon the Church, it beareth the name of an Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as generally whatſoever is offered to, or in that way ſettled upon the Church doth ſo. Secondly, <hi>propter praecedentem promiſsionem ſive deputationem:</hi> As when a man <hi>inter vivos</hi> engaged himſelf by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of beneficence to a Church,<note place="margin">Inſtit. l. <hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>7.</hi> de Donat.</note> or <hi>cauſâ mortis,</hi> did depute, deſtinate, or lay aſide any moveable thing for that purpoſe (<hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te tali voluntate</hi> unrevoked) it ought to be performed (every man in Law being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed<note n="*" place="margin">Gloſſ. in ver. Perdurare ca. Majores Ext. de Baptiſmo. <hi>13.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> c. Qui Oblatione &amp;c. Clerici &amp; <hi>16.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Statu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus &amp; Gloſſ. <hi>161.</hi> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cil. <hi>2.</hi> Turenenſ. c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Durare in voluntate in qua decedit</hi>) yea, the party or parties entruſted failing in the performance of the truſt in them repoſed <hi>tanquam egentium &amp; pauperum neca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores</hi> ſo are they accounted) to be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169004:63"/>Thirdly, <hi>propter neceſsitatem,</hi> as when the Miniſter had not wherewith to ſuſtain himſelf, the people were bound to ſupply.<note place="margin">Gloſſ. in v. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuus distinct. <hi>1.</hi> de Conſecrat. c. Omnis Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> And <hi>Bartholomaeus Brixienſis</hi> his Gloſſe upon the Text is, That if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſo to doe, the Miniſter being poor might cut them ſhort. <hi>Officia divina ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendo.</hi> The fourth and laſt is <hi>propter conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem,</hi> according to which the faithfull were tied <hi>certis feſtivitatibus,</hi> to make their accuſtomed Oblations. Now amongſt the Feſtivals the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> was, and worthily is a moſt ſpecial one. At which Feaſt there was even in many places here in <hi>England</hi> anciently an Oblation made by inferiour Churches and Pariſhes: to the principall mother Churches, which in probability may originally cauſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of <hi>Pentecoſtalia</hi> or <hi>Whitſun-far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things</hi> (for ſo alſo are they called) they being the iſſue perhaps of a devout Faſt and abſtinence, that about that time was by a Councel decreed to be kept; or of that great Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm yearly celebrated with much ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169004:63"/>at this Feaſt, and Eaſter only; at what time the people brought their children <hi>turmatim,</hi> by troups at it were, unto their Baptiſmal Churches to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, which Cuſtome continued not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the time of <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Firſt, as <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Rhenanus,</hi> but long after,<note place="margin">Rhenani obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat. in Tertul. fol. <hi>154.</hi> Abb. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rspergenſ. Chronicon.</note> even to the time of <hi>Lotharius</hi> the Second (that lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout four hundred years agoe) as <hi>Abbas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſpergenſis</hi> obſerves: Or rather perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture they allude to thoſe Oblations in the time of the Law which the Jews made at their anniverſary meetings in the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at this Feaſt. To the which Oblations they held themſelves bound by that place of Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.<note place="margin">Exod. 23.15. Deut. 16.16.</note> 
               <hi>Non apparebis in conſpectu Dei vacuus.</hi> So then, the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> being the Mother Church of the Jews, to which at this Feaſt they brought their Offerings: And our Cathedrals being (in a ſpecial manner though not only) the Mother Churches of particular Dioeceſes (to which at the ſame time Offerings have bin anciently brought, as before is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned)
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169004:64"/>this cuſtome of Pentecoſtall Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings may in ſome probability have its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal derivation thence. And in this gueſs <hi>Gulielmus Durandus</hi> runs along thus far in agreement with me. <hi>Ritus igitur</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Synagogae tranſivit in Religione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſiae, &amp; ſacrificia carnalis populi mutata ſunt in obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam populi ſpiritualis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Durand. Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale divinorum Offic. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi> Numb. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> Thus he, writing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the offerings of the old Law. And ſurely it is not vainly conceived, the Jews might be the Authors of this Cuſtome. Nor needs any man to be aſhamed to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their ſteps in ſo good an example, though the worſt of men, <hi>Gens ſceleratiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug de Civit. Dei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>11.</hi> Syneſ. in Epiſt. Epiſt. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> out of <hi>Seneca,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Syneſius</hi> pleaſeth to ſtile them. But to come back to our buſineſs. To the principall Mother-Churches then, theſe Oblations were eſpecially made, and being thither brought, the Biſhops as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſet forth and declared, had them ſolely to diſpoſe of, as whatſoever elſe were offered in or brought unto other Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal and Parochial Churches,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>16.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuimas.</note> yea and Chappels too (for in ſuch alſo Oblations
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169004:64"/>were made <hi>conſentiente Epiſcopo,</hi> &amp; not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) came within the compaſs of his diſtribution. So I find that <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Third did by his <hi>Dipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma</hi> or Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents grant the fourth part of the offerings made upon the greater Altar of the church of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baron. annal. ad ann. Chr. <hi>1153.</hi>
               </note> to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt and Canons of the ſame church. This of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>12.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. Epiſcopus.</note> And that the Biſhops elſewhere did or might doe the ſame, I ſee no cauſe to doubt, though the Pope whoſe power and authority in this Kingdome and elſewhere was once ſo great as being (forſooth) <hi>Caput omnium Pontificum a quo illi tanquam à capite membra deſcendunt,</hi> as <hi>Durandus</hi> overlaſheth;<note place="margin">Durand. Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtr. &amp; ordin. Eccl. l. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> and as having within the compaſs and limits of his juriſdiction above an hundred and twenty Archbiſhopricks, and above a thouſand Biſhopricks, as <hi>Stapleton</hi> vaunts,<note place="margin">Stapleton de Magnitud. Rom. Eccl. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> did <hi>ex plenitudine poteſtatis</hi> ſometimes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and order and diſpoſe things in the Church according to his own will, giving to this body, or that member as he ſaw cauſe; but ever to the Clergy to whom,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169004:65"/>and to thoſe uſes before expreſſed by the Canon Law theſe Offerings were and are only due, and otherwiſe interdicted to the Laity <hi>ſub diſtrictione Anathematis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Quia Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erdo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, &amp; e. Sanct. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trumibi.</note> And hence it may be that in ſome places the Deans and Praebendaries of Cathedral Churches have them. In other places Praebends are founded upon them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance two (if credible report deceive me not) in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> a greater and a leſſe diſtinguiſhed and known by this difference of <hi>Major &amp; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor pars Altaris.</hi> And in ſome Dioeceſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain they are ſettled upon the Biſhop and Archdeacon, and made part of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, for which the King hath Tenths and Subſidies. An inſtance hereof: The Cathedrall or mothrr Church of <hi>Worceſter</hi> was anciently before the diſſolution a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory; and among other Revenues belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſame Church it had thoſe <hi>Pentecostalia</hi> or Whitſun-farthings yearly brought unto it, under the name of Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or ſpirituall profits <hi>tempore Pentecoſtes.</hi> And after the Diſſolution: when King
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169004:65"/>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, about the 33 year of his reign did found anew and reendow the ſaid Church, he returned theſe <hi>Pentecoſtalia</hi> (after he had kept them about a year in his own hands) in expreſs terms back again to the ſaid Church, which the Dean and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries there receive unto this day (as I am informed) and appeareth due by the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Henricus Octavus,</hi> &amp;c. Sciatis quod nos de gratia noſtra ſpeciall, ac ex certa ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, ac me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o motu nostris dedimus &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſimus, ac per praeſentes damus &amp; concedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Decano &amp; Capitulo Eccleſiae cathedra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Chriſti, &amp; beatae <hi>Mariae</hi> Virginis <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorn.</hi> omnes illas Oblationes &amp; Obven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, ſive ſpiritualia p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oficua vulgariter vocat <hi>Whitſun-farthings</hi> annuatim, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. ſive recepta de diverſis villatis in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitat. noſtris <hi>Wigorn. Warwic.</hi> &amp; <hi>Heref.</hi> infra Archidiaconatum <hi>Wigorn.</hi> &amp; tempore Pentecost. oblata dicto nuper Prioratui b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atae <hi>Mariae Wigorn.</hi> modò diſſolut. dudum ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctan. &amp; pertinen. &amp;c. Ex Arch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Decani &amp; Capit. <hi>Wigorn.</hi>
               </note> Letters Patents. But in <hi>Gloucester</hi> it is otherwiſe; for there the Biſhop and Archdeacon only receive them; neither can the Dean and Prebendaries that now are of the Cathedral, nor could the Abbat &amp; Monks of that Church before them ever make juſt claim to them: For before the ſuppreſſion theſe <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſtals, inter alia,</hi> were valued to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon in the Kings books, as part of the revenue of the Archdeaconry, even when <hi>Procurations</hi> and <hi>Synodals</hi> were, and for ought I know to the Biſhop too; but I leave that to the Record, and would here end.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169004:66"/>But as he that after a long night deſires to behold the appearance of the morning Sun; ſo my ſelf, not yet ſufficiently ſatisfied with what hath been formerly produced in this obſcure paſſage, and deſirous <hi>vel in minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioribus</hi> to behold the brightneſs of truth, then which nothing can be more deſireable. Upon the apprehenſion of ſome conceived light beginning to diſcover it ſelf in this particular.
<q>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Euripid. in Phoeniſſ.</note>
               </q> 
               <hi>Hope to finde gives me encouragement, and makes me yet eager to ſeek. Fabianus</hi> a certain Biſhop moves two queſtions to Pope <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacius,</hi> which, as I conceive, doe ſomewhat concern our preſent buſineſs. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the two was,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. Nec numerus, &amp; Gloſſ. <hi>161.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Whether a Biſhop might require</hi> pro Cathedratico, ultra antiquam conſuetudinem? To this the Pope anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>no, he might not.</hi> And the later was this, <hi>What part of Oblations he ought to receive?</hi> And the Pope refers him to the Cuſtome obſerved in other Churches, whether a moytie or third part: Not the moity or
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169004:66"/>third part generally of all the Oblations made (that queſtionleſs is not the queſtion in this place) but only of ſuch as were brought in,<note place="margin">Polydor. Virg. de Invent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>8. 18</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> c. Fleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Diſtinct. <hi>1.</hi> c. Slennit. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onum.</note> 
               <hi>in die ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verſariae dedicationis</hi> (for this ſolemnity was annual, and all upon that day, <hi>vicatim</hi> made holy day, as <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> hath it) <hi>vel alterius ſolennitatis,</hi> as the Biſhop and Founder, or Prieſt did covenant and agree at the time of the Dedication of that Church; ſo the Gloſs explains the Caſe. And ſurely this is it that <hi>Hostienſis</hi> ſpecially aims at, if I miſtake not, when wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the time of the impoſition of Church Cenſes, he thus ſaith, That their impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was <hi>aut fundationis tempore, aut donatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, aut conſecrationis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Host. in ſumma de Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. § Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis Cenſus.</note> 
               <hi>aut tempore immunitatis indultae. His enim temporibus, vel imponitur, vel offertur</hi> ſaith <hi>Hoſtienſis.</hi> And probable it is, yea doubtleſs ſo it was:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>16.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi> c. Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque.</note> For as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Biſhops knowledge,<note place="margin">Platin. Volater. l. <hi>22.</hi> Et Polyd. Virgilubi ſupra. Bale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s de Rom. Pontiſ. de actis <hi>18.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> c. De Monachis.</note> and conſent <hi>praeter Praeſulis conſcientiam</hi> no Church could be conſecrated within a Dioeceſs (<hi>Faelix</hi> the third having made a Conſtitution to that purpoſe about the year 484) ſo neither could any Church or Monaſtery be found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169004:67"/>or built in a Dioeceſs without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of Epiſcopall approbation, except in places priviledged,<note place="margin">De Privilegiis c. Authoritate in <hi>6<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi>
               </note> exempted from the Biſhop, and appropriated to the Pope. So that when the Biſhop did yield his conſent to the founding, or his pains in conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or dedicating any ſuch Church, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſomewhat to himſelf and to his <hi>See Epiſcopal nomine Penſionis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ext. de Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſis domibus c. Conſtitutus.</note> 
               <hi>Sed nec illud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolitum aut novum habert debet, ut cum Epiſcopi Eccleſias piis locis ritè conceſſerint, aut exemptas fecerint aliquid ſibi in iis penſionis nomine reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</hi> Not that the Biſhop did ſtipulate or contract with any, either Founder or Prieſt, to receive ſo much <hi>in recompenſationem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſ. in v. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſationem. Ext. de eodem.</note> for ſuch his conceſſion, conſent or pains taking any way before hand, and that he would not doe it, <hi>niſi prius aliquid ex pacto detur, vel promittatur:</hi> No, that was held abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable as down-right Simony, a ſin (of any other deteſtable) and not only againſt the Decree of the Pope,<note place="margin">Ext. de Symo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia c. Tanta. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>4</hi> c. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia Concil. Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. <hi>4.</hi> Can. <hi>5.</hi> Aug. Epiſt. <hi>75.</hi> ad Aux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntium.</note> but the Canon of a Provinciall Councel (ſuch conſecration had been execration, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.) But when the buſineſs came to be
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169004:67"/>effected that was purſued, then was the reſervation made, it ſeemeth then. But here now falls in a queſtion, <hi>vtrum in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualibus interveniat Pactio?</hi> Oblations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpiritual Profits, it might be demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Whether they were ſettled at the firſt, where now for the moſt part they ſtick (namely in the Biſhop) and are rendred and paid under the name of <hi>Pentecoſtals,</hi> by a contract yea or no? To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Videtur quòd ſic.</hi> For in the Decree I find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chapter (to name but one) to this purpoſe. An Oratory was founded by the Mother of <hi>Eleutherius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>18.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> c. Eleutherius.</note> a Biſhop in the Dioeceſs of one <hi>Cardellus</hi> a Biſhop; at the Dedication of which Oratory there was a <hi>Conveniſſe,</hi> ſaith the Text, between the Foundreſs and the Biſhop, that ſuch a proportion the Biſhop ſhould have out of the Oblations made at ſuch a Feaſt. It ſeemeth then that contracts of this nature might be made. But whether this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniſſe,</hi> this Contract ought to be before or after the Dedication may admit ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtion. If after, the Gloſſe upon
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169004:68"/>the Chapter <hi>Eccleſia</hi> warranteth that <hi>poſt dedicationem paciſci Epiſcopo ſuggerente permitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi> c. Eccleſia.</note> ſo then the Biſhop might after De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication by way of pact require a Penſion. But might he not before? Yes, It is not doubted by the judicious, but affirmed that he uſually did and ought to doe ſo, which by no means he might doe if any corruption were in this contract. But contract I cannot ſo fitly call it: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit there be a kind of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance or ſeeming ſhew of a con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Biſhop and the Founder or Prieſt in this Act, yet in truth it cannot properly, and in ſtrictneſs of Law be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a contract. And ſo much the Gloſſe upon the Chapter <hi>Eleutherius</hi> doth plainly deliver in theſe words: <hi>Dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quòd hic non verè, dicitur pactum, quia &amp; ſine pacto tenetur Eccleſia aliquid dare Epiſcopo in ſignum ſubjectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> Thus then the Biſhop did reſerve a Penſion at the time of the foundation or dedication of the Churches within his Dioeceſs; and this he might lawfully doe without any the leaſt ſuſpition of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169004:68"/>And his Epiſcopal authority did not only warrant him to make ſuch reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to himſelf out of the church oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but to impoeſe a Cenſe upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any Church under his juriſdiction to the uſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron thereof, if need did require. <hi>Imo Epiſcopi authoritate poteſt aliquid conſtitui Patrono,</hi> as the Gloſs above mentioned hath it. And now at length to draw to a concluſion, the ſum of all is. This <hi>Pentecoſtal</hi> that I have been ſo long in ſeeking after, and is in common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt here in <hi>England</hi> at this day, is nothing elſe (as I conceive) but the annual comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration, continuation or repetition of an ancient payment, or penſion, iſſuing out of the oblations brought by the people ſo long agoe at the time ſpecially of the foundation or ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cation of their ſeveral Churches, or at ſome other ſolemnity, to wit, the moity or third part of the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions then made. The ſame being reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Biſhop, and by a contract <hi>(ſeu quaſi)</hi> between him and the Founder of ſuch Church or Prieſt, aſsigned to attend the ſame, ſetled in and upon the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169004:69"/>See, and payable yearly at or about the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pra <hi>10</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. Nec numerus.</note> for <hi>Alterius ſolennitatis</hi> will warrant ſuch a conjecture. This I ſay is, at leaſt I take to be the ſame that we now call by the name of <hi>Pentecoſtals</hi> or <hi>Whitſun-farthings.</hi> And ſo now, if truth fall out here alſo to be the iſſue, as it hath certainly been the object of theſe my weak endeavours, then have I that by Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour performed to me,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.7.</note> that ſometimes in Evangelical words was promiſed to a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant (whom <hi>Clemens Abexandrinus</hi> makes mention of) conſulting the Oracle how he might pleaſe his Maſter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>If thou ſeek thou ſhalt find</hi> ſaith the Oracle.<note place="margin">Clem. Alexand. <hi>4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Strom. ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim. ab initio.</note> But if miſapprehenſion or <hi>ſpecies recti</hi> inſtead of truth, miſinforming judgement hath run me into error (as it is eaſie for a ſtranger travelling in parts unknown and unfrequented ſometimes to ſtep aſide, and to be out of his way) My ſuit to the Reader then is —<hi>ſi quid noviſti rectius iſtis Candidus imperti:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat. Epiſtol. l. <hi>1.</hi> ad Numid.</note> which if he fail to do, and my ſelf not able to rectifie things amiſs, The Jewiſh extremity muſt be my refuge,<note place="margin">Buxtorf. de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vtaturis, pa. <hi>182.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tiſhbi ſolvat.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:169004:69"/>
            <head>An Appendix to the former Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſetting forth the reaſon of printing that and poſt-ſcribing this.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He precedent Treatiſe that now at length preſents it ſelf to publick view, hath lain written by me for divers years, and importunity that occaſioned the being that it hath could not fully effect what it willed, till an opportunity alſo (not expected) impoſed a production. Some few years agoe I had the collection of Procurations, and ſuch other rights and duties as have been anciently belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto, and are veſted in the Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conry of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> for the Archdeacon that now is there, as for many years I had before in his Predeceſſors time, my very
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169004:70"/>dear Friend. The harſh entertainment that I found from ſome of the Clergy upon the demand of Procurations for the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon in the year of the Metropoliticall viſitation of the L. Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> that now is, when by Sir <hi>Nathan Brent</hi> his Vicar-General he viſited the Dioeces of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> put me forward ſeriouſly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after the reaſon of that payment, but eſpecially of its due in the years of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal triennial viſitation, which though for many years it had been yearly without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſsion or interruption payd (acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances to that purpoſe I have by me of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 60. years antiquity, &amp; have ſeen ſome more ancient) yet was it then, even then vehemently oppugned. The Viſitation ended, &amp; my ſelf gotten out of the ſtorm, I adventured with ſuch poor faculties ad I had to make triall how farre forth I could be able to give ſatisfaction to thoſe that for the time to come ſhould require a reaſon of the payment, and travelling a while in this ſtudy, at laſt I caſt up the reckoning of my labour, and found
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169004:70"/>it to amount to this <hi>Qualecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſit</hi> (call it what you pleaſe) that goes before. And albeit in reſpect of the ſubject matter it may fall out to diſpleaſe ſome (I cannot avoid it) it comes ſo near the purſe: yet as of the Fig-tree 'tis obſerved, that though it be very bitter (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) produceth notwithſtanding ſweet fruit:<note place="margin">Plutar. <hi>5<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ. Probl. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> ſo if the groundwork of this Diſcourſe lie right (be the ſuperſtructure as it may) it will in the end doubtleſs prove profitable, how unpleaſing, how bitter ſoever it may ſeem for the preſent, by forewarning thoſe that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>able to ſuch payments to avoid op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that will neceſsitate both expenſe of time; time, I ſay (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tius in vita Theophraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> a preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and coſtly expenſe, as <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> was wont to ſay) yea, and ſomewhat elſe, though farre leſs in value, yet of no little account (eſpecially in theſe dayes) Money too; and if ſo, I ſhall be, I hope, diſtaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to none, nor (to ſpeak in the Apoſtles phraſe) <hi>become his enemy to whom I tell the truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 4.16.</note> For my part I thought it ſufficient (praiſe I ſeek not) to endeavor towards
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169004:71"/>the way of Pacification, it was, and is my only propoſed end. And however I may fall ſhort of the ſcope I aimed at, yet as in all acts Civil or Religious, or whatever elſe, <hi>velle,</hi> to be willing only (where abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is wanting) amounts to a perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance in acceptation; ſo I nothing fear the cenſure of the ingenuous and candid Reader whoſe charity receiving informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but from the rules of natural reaſon, hath learned him to excuſe imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with a
<q>Si deſunt vires tamen est laudanda voluntas.</q> But I wheel too far about. The occaſion of that Poſt-ſcript is briefly this, to wit a certain Manuſcript that is carried up and down, and paſſeth through many mens hands (I had only a curſory view of it, and that by chance) upon the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject with this of mine, but directly in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers material paſſages oppoſit to it. The Author of this book is or ſeems to be my friend; betwixt us for three or four years laſt paſt there hath continued an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:169004:71"/>of much familiarity, ſo far forth that each from other might challenge or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Courteſies. Now that which to me herein reliſheth ill, and in him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſeemeth <hi>abſonum,</hi> untunable and out of ſquare, and friendly compaſſe is; Firſt, that he having had the peruſal of thoſe Papers of mine ſo many weeks together, till he had tranſcribed them, and taking advantage, belike, from the inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or ſurmiſed partiality of my arguments which yet lay hidden and hurt no man) he, I ſay, ſhould without provocation write, and undertake to defend upon ſuppoſition of wrong (ſo it is preſented) ſuch a cauſe as neither hath, or ever ſhall wittingly, and <hi>de induſtriâ</hi> be impeached by my tongue or pen, namely the cauſe of the Clergy. I fear not to ſay (becauſe I can truly ſay) I know not, I thank God, to prevaricate, and hope never to be ſo unhappy as to learn. Secondly, and that which indeed is the All (if I may not be thought <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to meddle in a buſineſs wherin I have ſo little to doe,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169004:72"/>for now indeed I have not equall cauſe, nor like encouragement to write that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly I had) is this, That he goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by this book of his to alter, yea, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to a aboliſh a courſe of payment ſo long continued, by ſuggeſting out of the Canon Law, and Provincial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, that injury is done by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons (not viſiting and yet) requiring and receiving Procurations in the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall years of Viſitation; wherin I confeſs he hath done the Clergy either much good, or very bad ſervice. If his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be as prevalent as the title of his book is plauſible,<note place="margin">Clergy grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> I envy not unto him the praiſe of his good demerits (God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that error committed ſhould be either countenanced or continued, he deſerves recompence equivalent that diſcovers it) but if otherwiſe, thoſe that are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him may haply ſuffer by him (by his labour I mean) how zealous ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſeemeth to be in the Clergies cauſe. For the man, to give him his due, he is ingenuous, and not (as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaid
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169004:72"/>ſomewhere of <hi>Oſiander</hi>) <hi>futiliter,</hi> vainly or unprofitably. No, the contrary ſure, dexterous alſo in his employments, and of ready diſpatch. But I wiſh in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, being a buſineſs of moment and importance, that more conſideration had been taken before he had made it ſo publick, as it is, or importuned towards the Preſs to make it more. The <hi>Greeks</hi> amongſt them had a Law againſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pian in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Orat. An. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogit. p. <hi>380.</hi> apud Demoſthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that no Decree ſhould goe forth inconſiderately. So alſo had the Emperor <hi>Augustus</hi> a Speech which he fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently uſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Sueton. in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> implying that no determination could be unqueſtionably currant, that had not its ſettlement upon the baſis or bottom of mature and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate counſell. Had theſe or ſuch other leſſons to the ſame purpoſe (whereof there are many, which the wiſedome of former times hath adviſedly recorded, and recommended to poſterity for imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) been ſeriouſly thought on, this haſty onſet of my friend might have been forborn. Doubtleſs in this caſe he might
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169004:73"/>have done better to have ſpared his pains, I ſay in this caſe wherein, except error certain had been found (and then, as in civil broyls and diſcords <hi>facto potius quàm conſulto opus eſſet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit. <hi>1.</hi> Hiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</note> ſo down with ſuch a miſchief the faſter the better,<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſloph. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quil. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> then) there was no cauſe of oppoſition (on his part none) nor cauſe of haſte that I know. But to give my friend ſome little ſatisfaction, ſuch as I may, (and I hope he will not prove like him in the Comedy, not perſwaded though perſwaded;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoph. in Plut.</note> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive better of him then ſo) thus much I muſt ingenuouſly acknowledg. That in the Canon Law and Provinciall Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, from the letter of ſome few Texts and Gloſſes, ſuch a ſenſe, ſeeming at the leaſt, as he aſſerts doth reſult; namely, that Procurations are not otherwiſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired but upon the duty of Viſitation performed.<note place="margin">Extr. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tit. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> As for example, <hi>Procurationes quae ratione viſitationis debentur Epiſcopis, &amp;c. abſque manifestâ cauſâ nullatenus exigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, niſi quando perſonabiliter officium viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis impendunt.</hi> And again, <hi>Archidiaconis
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169004:73"/>districtius inhibemus ne aliquo modo Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones recipiant ſine cauſâ rationabili, niſi illo die quo perſonaliter viſitant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Provin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Const de oſſicio Archid</note> Such paſſages the Reader of our Laws will now and then meet withall. And from hence (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) it is, and from axioms not well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood (as that of <hi>Ceſſante cauſa ceſsat ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. adigere § Quamvis de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Patron. c. Cum ceſſante <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xtr. de appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat.</note> and ſuch like) that the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and conceipts of many (diving no deeper into the ſenſe and meaning of the Law then the <hi>ſuperficies</hi> or bare letter,<note place="margin">Gribald. de Rat. Stud. l. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> nor framing to themſelves any doubt which they ought to do before they can peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily decide) are invaded and whirled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with error. And ſuch I take this to be, That no Procuration can warrantably and with good conſcience be demanded without the act of Viſitation firſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by or in the perſon of him that makes ſuch claim. But if more could not be ſaid then this, that the Living of an Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con conſiſts of Procurations, for which he is accountable in reſpect of yearly pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the King (and this is ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready and ſeems not to ſatisfie) I ſuppoſe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169004:74"/>there were reaſon enough to plead a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome for the payment of them in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops triennial year <hi>ſine viſitatione</hi> on his part; otherwiſe it would fall out that the omiſſion of an act which he is forbidden to doe, would deſtroy an Office which the equity of the Law will not permit to be. Let the Caſe be paralleld. A Mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary is not properly and originally ſaid to be due to an Eccleſiaſticall Incumbent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Vicar from any but thoſe only of his own Pariſh to whom he miniſtreth ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual inſtruction, and hath right to their Tythes:<note place="margin">C. Statu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um v. ut inſra de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetud in Gloſſ. <hi>But ſee Sir</hi> H. Spelman <hi>his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture upon this point of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries in his Treatiſe</hi> de ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ltura. p. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lyndewoods</hi> Gloſſe upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall Conſtitutions, diſcovering the ground and reaſon of that payment to be this, namely, That when through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſometimes through negligence and unjuſt detention of Tythes and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Pariſhioner was found tardy and faulty, &amp;c. <hi>Ideo ſtatuit [Archiepiſcopus] quod compenſatione ſic ſubtractorum ſecundum meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us animal defuncti Eccleſiae damno debuit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicari.</hi> But all this notwithſtanding, we know the prevalency of Cuſtome to be
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169004:74"/>ſuch, that in ſome places of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they are paid to the Incumbents of other Pariſhes that perform no miniſteriall duties at all to the deceaſed party, nor li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nor dying.<note place="margin">21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> And the Statute doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all controll the courſe, but makes the uſage of payment only to be the Law thereof. Thus then, if the parallel come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing near the point, if it prove but <hi>argumentum a ſimili</hi> that known and common axiom of <hi>Bartolus</hi> may be pertinent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, which is this;<note place="margin">L. illud. ad l. Aquil.</note> 
               <hi>ubi militat eadem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, idem jus statui debet;</hi> and that other <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis identitas, non patitur deciſionem ſimilium caſuum eſse diverſam.</hi> But yet the mound is not made faſt enough, cavill will find or make way through. Lets look back again and examine the places above quoted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this payment, where we ſhall find the conſtitutions ſet down in terms of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification; <hi>Procurationes quae &amp;c. ſine manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta causâ:</hi> And what needs all this if there were not yet another right beſides the reaſon of Viſitation that inforceth this payment. But concerning this particular, having writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169004:75"/>ſomething in the foregoing Treatiſe, I reſolve in this place to ſay no more. Thus much only I will intimate to my friend, becauſe he ſhall wait no longer for my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion in this point. Let the places by him urged out of the Common Law and Provincial Conſtitutions,<note place="margin">C. 1. <hi>diſtinct.</hi> 11.</note> and Gloſſes, carry with him as much ſtrength as thoſe Laws may be imagined to be capable of, to prove and uphold his aſſertion; yet as the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts ſay of the Civil Law, that where it op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the Canon it is not to be regarded, that muſt give place to this, as they ſay: So, if any Canon or Conſtitution whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is with us of ſuch force (though I will yield them their due to the full) to annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and overthrow National Laws or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes;<note place="margin">Eut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op. l. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> That any Popes Decree or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript ſhould be like thoſe <hi>Edicta Praetoria,</hi> as the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.12.</note> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual, unalterable, and irrefragable; that he ſhould ſay, and all ſhould hearken and obey,<note place="margin">Diodor. Sicul. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> as it was ſaid of <hi>Iſis</hi> Queen of <hi>Aegypt, Quae ego legibus ſtatui nullus poterit ſolvere:</hi> I profeſs it comes not within the compaſs
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169004:75"/>of my Creed, nor have I faith to believe it. Thus much I have learned, which I alſo believe,<note place="margin">25 <hi>H.</hi> 8.<hi>c.</hi> 19. 1 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 1.</note> that ſuch and only ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and Conſtitutions as have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by general conſent and cuſtome within the Realm, and are not contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant or repugnant to the Laws, Statutes and Cuſtomes of the Realm,<note place="margin">Coke de jure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Eccleſiaſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, p. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> nor tend to the damage or hurt of the Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Royal, are in force within this Realm; as the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Lawes of the ſame, and none other. Now that ſuch Canon or Conſtitution Papal or Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial that neceſſarily ties the receiving of Procurations to the Act &amp; duty of Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only is repugnant, firſt to a Cuſtome grounded and preſcribed from a Record of good antiquity, and obſerved in divers Dioeceſſes of this Kingdome. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly to an Act of Parliament almoſt as ancient, that warrants ſuch a receit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mention of any Viſitation, is evident as by that which in the precedent Tractate hath been briefly intimated, ſo alſo by that which here follows, wherein both
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169004:76"/>Record and Act are more fully deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. The Record is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Archidiaconatus Glouc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Valet clarè in Proxis, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag. &amp; Pentecoſtal ibid.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>26</hi> H. <hi>8.</hi> Extract. è Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. Primitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> per annum ultra lx. s. ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut. pro feud.</hi> Raphael Rawlins <hi>Collect. dict. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Cenag cum Pentecoſtal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>64 <abbr>l.</abbr> 10 <abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>x<hi rend="sup">2</hi> inde</hi> 6 <abbr>l.</abbr> 9 <abbr>s.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Here is plainly ſet down the true worth and full value of the Archdeaconry of <hi>Gl.</hi> in Procurations, Synodals and Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſtals, to wit 64 <abbr>l.</abbr> 10 <abbr>s.</abbr> And for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of future cavil (as if the preſent oppoſition had been ſo many years agoe foreſeen) it is expreſſed <hi>per annum</hi> too (for thats the matter of grievance) ſo much yearly worth. And what would we more to make the matter plain? He doth in my opinion little other then <hi>Nodum in
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169004:76"/>ſcirpo quaerere,</hi> and conſequently beat the aire, that uſeth means to evade a pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo apparently clear and evident. Add to all this continual perception and collection of theſe duties by Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, even from the time of the valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them <hi>in Anno</hi> 26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. unto this preſent, and tenths, as before I have ſaid, paid out of them yearly to the Crown for all that time (I ſuppoſe there is none alive that can contradict it, <hi>et quod non diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatur praeſumitur</hi>) ſuch Books and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances as I have ſeen (and I have ſeen ſome that are ancient) all teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame. Beſides I never heard of any that ſtood out a ſuit againſt this pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that upon a judiciall hearing or trial ever prevailed in the principal cauſe and point of right, but was alwayes over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown in the litigation, and comepelled to pay charges.</p>
            <p>And as for the Act of Parliament, Thus much I find conducing to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>in Anno</hi> 34 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</p>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:169004:77"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IF any perſon or perſons being Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer or Occupier of any Manors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Raſtal. Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Penſions.</note> 
               <hi>Lands, Tenements, Parſonages, Benefices, or other Hereditaments of any of the ſaid late Monaſteries or Eccleſiaſticall houſes or places, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them or any of them by the Kings Highneſs gift, grant, ſale, exchange or otherwiſe, out of which premiſſes any ſuch Penſions, Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Corrodies, Indemnities, Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or Proxies or any other profits have been heretofore lawfully going out, anſwered or paid to any of the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-ſaid; doe at any time after the firſt day of</hi> April <hi>next comming, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deny the payment thereof, at the dayes of payment heretofore accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of any of the ſaid Penſions Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Corrodies, Indemnities, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodies, Proxies or any other profits, whereof the ſaid Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Archdeacons, or other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical perſons were in poſſeſſion at,
<pb n="014" facs="tcp:169004:77"/>or within ten years next before the time of the Diſſolution of any ſuch Monaſtery, or other Eccleſiaſtical houſes or places: that then it ſhall be lawfull for the ſame Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, or other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons aforeſaid, being ſo denied to be ſatisfied and paid there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and having right to the ſame thing in demand, to make ſuch proceſs as well againſt every ſuch perſon and perſons as ſhall ſo deny payment of the ſame Penſions, Portions, Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Proxies, Indemnities, Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or any other profits which of right ought to be paid, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as againſt the Church or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches charged with the ſame, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore they have lawfully done, and as by and according to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm they may now lawfully doe for the true payment and recovery thereof. And if the party Defendant be lawfully convict in any ſuch ſuit, cauſe or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, according to the Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169004:78"/>Lawes, then the party Plaintiffe ſhall have and recover againſt the party Defendant the thing in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and the value thereof in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, with his coſts for his Suit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By this Act it is plain that all ſuch pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as iſſued out of Parſonages, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices or other Hereditaments of the ſaid late Monaſteries to any Archbiſhop, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Archdeacon, &amp;c. at or within ten years next before the time of the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, ſhould be ſtill continued and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paid as before. Now the Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Proxies were yearly due,<note place="margin">The Record hath its ground from an Act of Parliament of 26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. The ſuppreſſion of Abbies follows in 31 <hi>ejuſdem Regis.</hi>
               </note> and paid within leſſe then ſix years before the Diſſolution, appeareth plainly by the preceding Record. Therefore yet to be paid according to the fore-recited Act.</p>
            <p>But perhaps it will be objected, Why was there a Proviſion made by Act of Parliament for payment of theſe duties out of Parſonages, &amp;c. belonging unto Monaſteries, and not out of others in
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169004:78"/>like manner in the then poſſeſsion of ſpirituall Incumbents? I anſwer; It ſeems to me that this <hi>Proviſo</hi> was made by the clemency of the King, and the indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Parliament to ſecure the rights of the Church to the true owners there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that haply might be paſſed away, and in hazard to be utterly loſt by the Kings Grant to Lay-perſons. And this to be the ground and reaſon of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is clearly demonſtrated in the latter part of the ſame Act of 34. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. where there is a courſe preſcribed how ſuch perſons in ſuch Caſes ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and in what Court they ſhould commence ſuit for the recovery of their ſubtracted rights, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Court of Augmentation of the Revenue of the Kings Crown, and not elſewhere. Theſe be the words of the Act whereunto I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the Reader. Now there needed no ſuch Act or caution as before is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; no ſuch <hi>Proviſo</hi> to ſecure the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors duties from the invaſion of ſpiritual Incumbents, of whoſe Promotions or
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:169004:79"/>Benefices the King made no ſale, nor medled withal, but left them entire, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to himſelf upon the return of the Certificate of their true value only an yearly Tenth, but with an exact deduction firſt of all ſuch ſumme or ſummes of money, Procurations, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe he then found them yearly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged withall: which being ſo allowed to the ſpirituall Incumbent, I conceive that thoſe that the Lawes and Statutes of this Realm have qualified and made capable of ſuch receits (and ſuch are Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, &amp;c.) may lawfully at their reſpective accuſtomed times, according to the fore-recited Act, require, and ſo ought to receive them, till authority ſhall alter the courſe. But to this point I hope there is enough ſaid already.</p>
            <p>To draw now towards a concluſion. Theſe Reaſons that I have here urged, together with thoſe formerly mentioned, make me to think that Procurations are not payable, as my friend thinks, <hi>Ratione
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:169004:79"/>lummodo viſitationis;</hi> no, but ſometimes Cuſtome hath its place, as all Canoniſts that I have read upon the point doe una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly acknowledge: yea, thoſe or ſuck like reaſons moved a very learned Civilian, Dr. <hi>Coſens,</hi> ſometime Dean of the Arches, writing of the quality of rights Eccleſiaſtical, and how they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came due amongſt other things, ſaith,<note place="margin">D Coſen. Polit. Eccleſiae Angl. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ab. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Penſiones indemnitatis Procurationes ratione vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitationis</hi> PLERUNQ. <hi>praeſtandae.</hi> He doth not ſay as my friend ſaith, that they are only ſo due, but <hi>Plerun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> ſo. Now what <hi>Plerun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> ſignifies is a little to be enquired after: That it comes near to the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication which correſponds to his fancy, no Grammarian I am ſure will allow. <hi>Plerun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> is never found to carry the ſenſe that <hi>ſolummodò</hi> doth; but that it yieldeth the ſame ſenſe and ſignification that <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> doth, Civilians well know,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian. l. Falſus ff. de Furt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> and I acknowledge. And in ſo doing I render him but ſmall advantage, and my ſelf as little prejudice. I hold my aſſertion ſtill. There is <hi>jus conſuetudinarium,</hi> a right of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:169004:80"/>by which Procurations are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ought (as I ſuppoſe) ſo to be. And the ſole reaſon of that payment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth not upon the Act of Viſitation only, &amp; alwaies as my friend would have it. I have done with this buſineſs. God grant that what it aims at it may effect. Peace, peace I ſay, either by ſubmitting to Truth, or convincing by Truth. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:169004:80"/>
            <p>LEt the Reader be pleaſed to take notice (as fit to be known) that the aforegoing Diſcourſe and Appendix were written in the time of Dr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> late Archdeacon of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> deceaſed, and not altered in this Impreſſion from what they then were (examined and prepared in Order to the Preſſe) except the miſtakes in Printing, of which the moſt material I have here no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; others of miſpointing and miſaccenting, with ſome other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral eſcapes; I pray the courteous Reader to make uſe of his Pen to amend, or his Patience to forbear what's amiſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page 7. line 4. read</hi> came <hi>Pa. 9. l. 11. r.</hi> us. <hi>Pa. 10. l. 21. r.</hi> Lions. <hi>Pa. 19. l. 3. 1.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Pa. 23. l. 16. r.</hi> Praelatus. <hi>Pa. 24. l. 16. r</hi> payment. <hi>Pa. 26. l. 8. r.</hi> ſubſistit. <hi>Pa. 26. l. 15. r.</hi> praeſcripta. <hi>Pa. 31. l. 13. r.</hi> is. <hi>&amp; l. 24. r.</hi> imputari. <hi>Pa. 85. l. 21. r.</hi> Parochial, <hi>and ſo elſewhere. Pa. 90. l. 6. r.</hi> riſe. <hi>Pa. 126. l 6. r.</hi> Nathaniel. <hi>Pa 128. l. 15. r.</hi> this. <hi>Pa. 132. l. 24, r.</hi> perſonaliter. <hi>Pa. 136. l. 6. r.</hi> Canon.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
